<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine contentment, or, A medicine for a discontented man and a confession of faith, and other poems upon several subjects / by Edward Manlove ...</title>
            <author>Manlove, Edward, fl. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11781410</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11781410</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49076</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49076)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1487:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine contentment, or, A medicine for a discontented man and a confession of faith, and other poems upon several subjects / by Edward Manlove ...</title>
                  <author>Manlove, Edward, fl. 1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Mills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>"Poems against popery" has its own t.p. on p. [75]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:1"/>
                  <p>Imprimatur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Ex Aedib. Lamb.</hi> 
                        <date>March. 6. 1666/7</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:1"/>
                  <p>DIVINE Contentment: OR A MEDICINE for a Diſcontented Man: AND A Confeſſion of FAITH: And other POEMS upon ſeveral SUBJECTS.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>EDWARD MANLOVE</hi> of <hi>Aſhborne</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby</hi> ESQUIER.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, for <hi>Richard Mills</hi> at the Peſtel and Mortar without <hi>Temple Barr.</hi> 1667.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:2"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <l>REad, and peruſe, this Poem to prevent,</l>
                  <l>The prejudice, that comes by Diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Which is a Sin not only Capitall,</l>
                  <l>But Catholick, and Epidemicall,</l>
                  <l>Both to, and fro, man's toſs'd, with diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Filld with diſquiet, and diſtemperment.</l>
                  <l>He's full of murmuring, nothing doth him pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>His reſtleſs ſpirit's, like the rageing Seas,</l>
                  <l>Alwaies tempeſtuous, full of rage and heat,</l>
                  <l>Often perplexed, with amazements great.</l>
                  <l>His troubled heart, is like a little Hell,</l>
                  <l>Wher's diſcontent; the Divel loves to dwell.</l>
                  <l>Then ſtrive O man, againſt this mortal ſin;</l>
                  <l>Prize contentation; Peace is found therein.</l>
                  <l>Peruſe this Poem; dreſt in mean attire,</l>
                  <l>Let true Contenment, be thy hearts deſire.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>EDW. MANLOVE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:3"/>
                  <head>A MEDICINE for a Diſcontented MAN.</head>
                  <byline>By <hi>Edward Manlove</hi> of <hi>Aſhborn</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby</hi> Eſquier.</byline>
                  <l>CAſt off diſtruſtful, and diſtracting care,</l>
                  <l>The love of Riches, brings a ſudden ſnare.</l>
                  <l>If with thy Wealth, thou do diſhonour God,</l>
                  <l>Twill ſurely haſten, his Correcting Rod,</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou be Rich? <hi>Paul</hi> for thy pattern take;</l>
                  <l>Learn thou Contentment, in a low eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Content's great gain, unto a godly ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Run faſt, make haſt, to get this Glorious Goale.</l>
                  <l>Engrave this leſſon on thy humble heart,</l>
                  <l>Lay out thy ſelf, and labour for this Art.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49076:4"/>
                  <l>The way to get it; may be beſt diſcern'd,</l>
                  <l>By Gods good word, this leſſon, there is learnd.</l>
                  <l>Then read, and hear, the Goſpel full of Grace,</l>
                  <l>In this tranſparent glaſs, behold Gods face.</l>
                  <l>When read, and heard, remember this thing more,</l>
                  <l>Safe in thy heart, this ſacred treaſure ſtore.</l>
                  <l>This truth's a treaſure, all men cannot get;</l>
                  <l>Then lay it up, in thy cheif Cabinet.</l>
                  <l>And prize it high, preſerve it for thy need,</l>
                  <l>To curb thy ſin, for thou art <hi>Adam's</hi> ſeed.</l>
                  <l>And many Luſts, from thy corrupted heart,</l>
                  <l>Wage dayly warre, againſt thy better part.</l>
                  <l>Then ſtoutly ſtrive, the maſterſhip to win,</l>
                  <l>Not by thy ſtrength, thou art a ſink of ſin.</l>
                  <l>By prayers, and tears, ſeek thou for help to him,</l>
                  <l>That can both help, and pardon all thy ſin.</l>
                  <l>O murmure not; but meekly walk with God,</l>
                  <l>Make bare thy back; if he lift up the Rod.</l>
                  <l>And be content; to (his) ſubmit thy will:</l>
                  <l>For he can ſweeten, every bitter Pill.</l>
                  <l>If thy condition, bitter ſeem, to thee,</l>
                  <l>Yet be content; it comes by Gods decree;</l>
                  <l>Who knowes thy ſtate; and eke this precept gave,</l>
                  <l>Content your ſelves, with ſuch things as ye have.</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt obey Gods word, it is his will;</l>
                  <l>At his command, the rageing Sea ſtood ſtill.</l>
                  <l>He is thy King; a Loyal Subject be,</l>
                  <l>Submit unto, his Royal Majeſtie.</l>
                  <l>If thou be poor, and pinch'd with Povertie,</l>
                  <l>Thy God is rich, and can provide for thee.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49076:4"/>
                  <l>Haſt thou no moneys, goods, nor earthly ſoyle?</l>
                  <l>God can ſuſtein thee, with a Cruce of Oyle.</l>
                  <l>Haſt no Eſtate, thy Children may poſſeſs?</l>
                  <l>God is a Father to the fatherleſs</l>
                  <l>Haſt nothing left, for thy beloved Wife?</l>
                  <l>Leave her to God, he can preſerve her life.</l>
                  <l>Art thou in pain? thy God can give thee eaſe,</l>
                  <l>And in thy ſickneſs, make thy ſickneſs ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>Art thou in Priſon? God can thee releaſe,</l>
                  <l>Art ſpoyl'd with Warre? thy God can ſend thee peace.</l>
                  <l>But for the preſent, learn to be content</l>
                  <l>Repine at nothing, Providence hath ſent,</l>
                  <l>Art thou plac'd in, a high, or lower Sphere?</l>
                  <l>It is God's Providence, that plac'd thee there.</l>
                  <l>If thou be placed, in the loweſt Orb,</l>
                  <l>Submit with Patience, to the living Lord,</l>
                  <l>God ſees it good, thou ſhouldſt be placed there,</l>
                  <l>Elſe he would place thee, in a higher Sphere,</l>
                  <l>The higheſt Orb, is not the ſafeſt ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Low ſhrubs are quiet, when high Cedars ſhake.</l>
                  <l>Are many Rich, and no Affliction feel?</l>
                  <l>And thou but poor, obſerve the inner wheel.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ezekiel</hi> minds thee of more wheels then one.</l>
                  <l>The inner wheel, turns all, or elſe turns none.</l>
                  <l>Gods providence, the inner wheel and beſt,</l>
                  <l>Doth ſtrongly move, and turneth all the reſt.</l>
                  <l>It is the Helme, that turns about the Ship,</l>
                  <l>The Vniverſe, is overrul'd by it.</l>
                  <l>And yet its compaſs, it doth not exceed,</l>
                  <l>But doth concurr, to perfect what's decree'd.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49076:5"/>
                  <l>Let thou, and I, this leſſon learn from hence;</l>
                  <l>Strive not at all, againſt God's providence.</l>
                  <l>But be contented, with thy preſent lott,</l>
                  <l>The wheel may turn, although thou knowſt it not</l>
                  <l>Let God chooſe for thee, be not over nice,</l>
                  <l>Leſt (<hi>Adam</hi> like) thou make an evil choice.</l>
                  <l>He had great choice, excepted was one tree,</l>
                  <l>He are of that, was curſt, and ſo were we.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lott</hi> made his choice, he had his hearts deſire,</l>
                  <l>He <hi>Sodome</hi> choſe, which ſoon was burnt with fire.</l>
                  <l>Remember <hi>Rachel,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Iacobs</hi> wife,</l>
                  <l>Her choice was Children, one coſt her, her life.</l>
                  <l>Take what God gives, let that give thee content,</l>
                  <l>God can ſupply thee, when thy ſtore is ſpent,</l>
                  <l>If God give more, beware of wilful waſt,</l>
                  <l>If God give leſs, praiſe God for what thou haſt.</l>
                  <l>By providence, mans life, preſerved is,</l>
                  <l>More then by Wealth, which is the worldlings bliſs</l>
                  <l>The quiet mind, in the contented man,</l>
                  <l>Yeeldeth more comfort, then his Riches can.</l>
                  <l>It makes him happy, cheatful, yea (content)</l>
                  <l>Makes Poor men Rich, when all their Treaſures ſpen</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent diſturbs, turns peace, to ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>It doth eate up, the comfort of mans life,</l>
                  <l>This inbred thief, doth rob us, of no leſs,</l>
                  <l>Then all the Riches, that we do poſſeſs</l>
                  <l>This bitter Dram, imbitters all the cup,</l>
                  <l>This ſowre ſop, all ſweetneſs drinketh up.</l>
                  <l>This fretting moth; doth fret the pureſt part,</l>
                  <l>This eating Canker; eats the very heart,</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49076:5"/>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou have comfort? baniſh diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or it doth cloud, thy comforts eminent.</l>
                  <l>But true content, doth all to comfort turn,</l>
                  <l>This Oyle keeps in the Lamp, and makes it burn.</l>
                  <l>Then pump thy heart, draw out all diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Stop up the leak, the danger to prevent.</l>
                  <l>For troubled waters, if they do get in</l>
                  <l>May drownd thy ſhip, and ſink thy ſoul in ſin,</l>
                  <l>This diſcontent, the better to avoid,</l>
                  <l>Be humble (man) and eke beware of Pride,</l>
                  <l>With that condition, God hath plac'd thee in,</l>
                  <l>Be thou content; for diſcontent is ſin.</l>
                  <l>Keep to thy calling, think it not too low,</l>
                  <l>Tax not God's wiſdome, he hath made it ſo.</l>
                  <l>Art thou a Tradeſman? follow then thy Trade,</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Adam</hi> (he) deſpiſed not a ſpade.</l>
                  <l>Our father <hi>Iacob,</hi> kept his fathers ſheep,</l>
                  <l>Where God hath plac'd thee, there thou ought's to keep</l>
                  <l>But now a daies, this diſcontent, and pride,</l>
                  <l>Makes many a man, his calling lay aſide,</l>
                  <l>It is too low or he too high for it,</l>
                  <l>This Pride makes him, his lawful calling quit,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrange Cameraes do poſſeſs his brain,</l>
                  <l>He ſeeks for ſomething in a higher ſtrain.</l>
                  <l>The Cobler then; the Pulpit needs muſt climbe,</l>
                  <l>His words are loſty, and his thoughts ſublime,</l>
                  <l>The Spirit moves him, how can he miſtake?</l>
                  <l>His words are ſtiched well and well they take,</l>
                  <l>He is improv'd, and you ſhall hear anon,</l>
                  <l>He's Paſtor of, ſome Congregation,</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49076:6"/>
                  <l>His purblind brethren, love to hear him teach,</l>
                  <l>And this proud Patcher, he preſumes to Preach.</l>
                  <l>And when he doth, this new found way forſake,</l>
                  <l>'Tis doubt he will, begin to Rant, or Quake.</l>
                  <l>Alas he's gone, ſo far beyond his Laſt,</l>
                  <l>He's like to fall, by running over faſt.</l>
                  <l>Pride puff'd him up, the Cobler climing high,</l>
                  <l>Ape like, hath ſhewd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his great'ſt deformity</l>
                  <l>Alas poor man! tis time that all lament,</l>
                  <l>Tis much adoe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for man to be content.</l>
                  <l>If he be poor; then envious he will be,</l>
                  <l>If Rich, puff'd up with his Proſperity.</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Iacobs</hi> Talent, learn to be content.</l>
                  <l>Praiſe God that hath, thee, food, and raiment, ſent</l>
                  <l>If thou be Rich, and yet doſt covet more,</l>
                  <l>It better is, to be content and poor.</l>
                  <l>Or if thy Riches, fill with worldly care,</l>
                  <l>Thy empty heart, thy riches are a ſnare,</l>
                  <l>Or if thy riches, cauſe thy diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Thy riches are, an empty Complement.</l>
                  <l>But art thou rich; and godly, and content?</l>
                  <l>Thy riches are, a gratious ſuppliment.</l>
                  <l>If thou imploy them, for Gods glory then,</l>
                  <l>God will thoe bleſs; thou wilt have praiſe of men.</l>
                  <l>Pray not for Riches, nor for Poverty,</l>
                  <l>But food convenient, that is beſt for thee,</l>
                  <l>A mean eſtate; may yeild as much content,</l>
                  <l>As Riches great, or places eminent.</l>
                  <l>Sorrow ſometimes, far better is then joy,</l>
                  <l>A low eſtate, far better then a high.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49076:6"/>
                  <l>What greater Honour, canſt thou do to God,</l>
                  <l>Then with ſubmiſſion, humbly kiſs his Rod?</l>
                  <l>Then be content, in want learn to abound,</l>
                  <l>This ſweet condition, is with comfort crownd.</l>
                  <l>Contentment here, the firſt fruit of Heaven is,</l>
                  <l>But true content, is in eternal bliſs.</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent, doth diſcompoſe the heart,</l>
                  <l>Doth gaul the ſpirit, vexeth every part.</l>
                  <l>It is a Gangrein, and a feſtring ſore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t turns both faith, and patience forth adore,</l>
                  <l>It is a breed bate, making jars, and fractions,</l>
                  <l>It fumes, it frets, it ſtirreth up, diſtractions.</l>
                  <l>It hurts the body, it, diſjoynts the ſoul,</l>
                  <l>It, makes ill, worſe, it is a Kindle coal.</l>
                  <l>It makes repining, when we ſhould rejoyce,</l>
                  <l>It, alwaies wants, it's full of avarice.</l>
                  <l>It, is a paſſion, that doth often robb,</l>
                  <l>Man of his reaſon; makes him ſlight his God,</l>
                  <l>But true contentment, in the inner part,</l>
                  <l>Workes trouble out, of every troubled heart;</l>
                  <l>As Phyſick doth, Diſeaſes purge away,</l>
                  <l>So doth contentment, greateſt gains alay.</l>
                  <l>It doth refreſh, and chear, the fainting heart,</l>
                  <l>Of every one, that gains this godly Art.</l>
                  <l>It makes the Lame, to leap, the Sad, to Sing;</l>
                  <l>Divine Contentment, doth ſweet ſolace bring.</l>
                  <l>There is great Virtue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Divine Content,</l>
                  <l>This Golden Shield, beats back diſcouragement,</l>
                  <l>This gallant ſhip, the heart from ſincking ſaves,</l>
                  <l>And makes it Sail above the rageing Waves.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49076:7"/>
                  <l>This true Content, doth ſet mans heart in tune,</l>
                  <l>By fervent Prayer, his God to importune.</l>
                  <l>It brings the heart, into a holy frame,</l>
                  <l>For God accepts, no Sacrifice that's lame.</l>
                  <l>Content breeds courage, in a godly Saint,</l>
                  <l>He beares his burden, when the wicked faint,</l>
                  <l>If God command him, he takes up his Croſs,</l>
                  <l>And by Contentment; he, makes gain of loſs,</l>
                  <l>Impatience, and diſcontent, are Twins</l>
                  <l>But true Content, doth baniſh theſe two ſins.</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent, much murmuring doth produce,</l>
                  <l>To let in ſin, it, is the very ſluce.</l>
                  <l>This murmuring ſin, the Divels Muſick is,</l>
                  <l>He likes no Tune, ſo well, as he likes this.</l>
                  <l>This Diſcontent, a reſtleſs Spirit is,</l>
                  <l>That haunts ſo many, and ſo few doth miſs,</l>
                  <l>It makes a man, means indirect to uſe,</l>
                  <l>To get ſuch things, as Nature bids him chooſe.</l>
                  <l>Contentment doth, temptations ſtrong prevent,</l>
                  <l>Though th' World, and fleſh, and Devil all do temp</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent, made <hi>Iob's</hi> wife fooliſh be</l>
                  <l>Unto her Husband ſay, <hi>Curſe God and die,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This diſcontent, a man an Atheiſt makes,</l>
                  <l>He turns Apoſtate, and his God forſakes.</l>
                  <l>He thinks that God, of man doth take no care,</l>
                  <l>He's not contented, with his Bill of Fare.</l>
                  <l>He nothing wants, and yet is diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>He hath enough, and yet is indigent,</l>
                  <l>Out of the Bloſſome, of this diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Growes bitter Fruit, an evil conſequent,</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49076:7"/>
                  <l>But with content; a little, is enough,</l>
                  <l>This Anchor ſtaies, the Ship; when ſtorms are rough</l>
                  <l>This turns the bitter water, into Wine,</l>
                  <l>And makes it taſt, the Nectar, from the Vine.</l>
                  <l>This Croſſes great, to Comforts great, doth turn,</l>
                  <l>And makes him merry, that before did mourn.</l>
                  <l>It makes his heavy burden, ſeem but light,</l>
                  <l>He hopes for Glory of a greater weight,</l>
                  <l>If this be then, the fruit of contentation,</l>
                  <l>O labour man, to get this conſolation.</l>
                  <l>This Honey Comb, drops ſweetneſs every where,</l>
                  <l>This comfort laſts, becauſe content is there,</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent, a ſowre Leaven is,</l>
                  <l>Our greateſt comforts, are Eclipſt by this;</l>
                  <l>It leſſens mercy, trebbles every Croſs,</l>
                  <l>Turns ſweet to ſowre, the pureſt Gold to droſs.</l>
                  <l>But true contentment, waits on Providence,</l>
                  <l>And takes God's dealings, in a better ſence.</l>
                  <l>If God ſend ſickneſs, Pain, or Poverty,</l>
                  <l>All's for the beſt, if thou contented be.</l>
                  <l>Doth God Refine thee, in a Furnace hot,</l>
                  <l>To purge away thy droſs, why ſhould be not?</l>
                  <l>Thou art his Gold, he makes thee ſparkle more,</l>
                  <l>Thou art made purer, then thou waſt before,</l>
                  <l>He in his Wiſdome, makes thy body ſmart,</l>
                  <l>To bring thee to, a better frame of heart.</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou be Rich, be ſure that Chriſt be thine</l>
                  <l>Of Grace and Wiſdome, he's the golden Mine.</l>
                  <l>He is a Pearle, a ſparkling Diamond,</l>
                  <l>His worth, all worldly Treaſure, goes beyond.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49076:8"/>
                  <l>Sell all thou haſt, to get this pretious prize,</l>
                  <l>And buy the Feild, wherein this Treaſure lies.</l>
                  <l>In Chriſt both Fulneſs and true Riches is,</l>
                  <l>By this inriching Pearl, comes glorious Bliſs.</l>
                  <l>Induring Riches, in this Treaſury,</l>
                  <l>Are locked up, from all Eternity.</l>
                  <l>If worldly Wealth be wanting, live by Faith</l>
                  <l>He that hath Chriſt; the greateſt Treaſure hath.</l>
                  <l>This, richly decks, the Soul; with true content.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the Riches, that are permanent.</l>
                  <l>If thou be rich and yet thy ſoul be poor,</l>
                  <l>What art thou better for thy worldly ſtore?</l>
                  <l>But if thy Soul beſpangled be with Grace</l>
                  <l>Thou art prepared, for a better place,</l>
                  <l>The high Plantation, Heavens Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>The glorious Heaven of Eternal Joyes.</l>
                  <l>There are true Riches, there's true conſolation,</l>
                  <l>There is full freedome, from all Reprobation,</l>
                  <l>All other things, are like the Butterfly,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Wings are painted, very curiouſly,</l>
                  <l>Yet touch them, they thy fingers do defile,</l>
                  <l>All Earthly things, are apt thy ſoul to ſoyle.</l>
                  <l>They do corrupt, they cannot long endure,</l>
                  <l>Fix not thy heart on things that are impure.</l>
                  <l>But be content, let God thy portion be,</l>
                  <l>He hath a godly heritage for thee.</l>
                  <l>The world is empty, only full of ſin,</l>
                  <l>In God is fulneſs, make addreſs to him,</l>
                  <l>He can give Riches, he can make thee poor,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> loſt much wealth, yet God did give him more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49076:8"/>
                  <l>Then do not kick, againſt the Lords decree.</l>
                  <l>He knowes thy ſtate, and knowes what's beſt for thee</l>
                  <l>Submit to God, imbrace his bleſſed Son,</l>
                  <l>Pray as he taught, (O Lord) thy will be done.</l>
                  <l>God is well pleaſed, with his Children, when</l>
                  <l>They like that portion, he allots to them.</l>
                  <l>He hath his end, in that they do ſubmit,</l>
                  <l>To Providence, and Acquieſs in it.</l>
                  <l>Then be content, to Satan do deſpight,</l>
                  <l>In diſcontent the Devil doth delight.</l>
                  <l>All evil paſſions, labour to prevent,</l>
                  <l>Diſpleaſe the Divel, learn to be content.</l>
                  <l>By diſcontent, the Devil's gratifi'd,</l>
                  <l>And by this ſin, thy Soul may be deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>Take heed of diſcord, tis the Devils joy,</l>
                  <l>Fly diſcontent, it brings much miſery.</l>
                  <l>Subdue thy ſelf, ſtrive for this Victory,</l>
                  <l>Keep down thy fleſh, it is an enemy.</l>
                  <l>Art thou reproached, or in Priſon caſt?</l>
                  <l>Bear it with patience till the ſtorm be paſt,</l>
                  <l>God can repair thee, and releaſe thee thence,</l>
                  <l>But he is pleas'd, to prove thy Patience.</l>
                  <l>He knowes what's in thee, but this exerciſe,</l>
                  <l>Will make thee learn, his mercy more to prize,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> was corrected with a ſharper rod,</l>
                  <l>Yet under ſufferings, he did Worſhip God.</l>
                  <l>He loſt both Flocks and Heards, and Children dear,</l>
                  <l>Yet in all this, he did God's Juſtice clear.</l>
                  <l>He was Diveſted, of a great Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>The Lord that gave, the Lord away did take.</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49076:9"/>
                  <l>His body ſuffered, in a high degree,</l>
                  <l>From Biles and Botches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there was no place free,</l>
                  <l>Then he a Potſheard, took himſelfe to ſcrape,</l>
                  <l>And humbly he, down in the aſhes ſate.</l>
                  <l>O here behold; the fruit of true content;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> ſuffered much, and yet was Patient.</l>
                  <l>He got much Gain, by this correcting Rod,</l>
                  <l>All works for good, to them that love their God.</l>
                  <l>God in his Wiſdome; maketh many times</l>
                  <l>Our Maladies, to be our Medicines.</l>
                  <l>Art thou then poor? are Earthly comforts gone?</l>
                  <l>God can make Phyſick, of Affliction.</l>
                  <l>Unto the Righteous; godly, and upright,</l>
                  <l>In greateſt darkneſs, there ariſeth light;</l>
                  <l>Afflictions great, may prove an excellent</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cathalicon</hi> againſt thy diſcontent.</l>
                  <l>And alſo teach thee, much Humility,</l>
                  <l>For much proud fleſh, within thy heart doth lie.</l>
                  <l>But ſharp corrections, are Gods Corrowſives,</l>
                  <l>To eat it out; proud fleſh is apt to riſe.</l>
                  <l>Yea Gall and Wormwood, God doth oft provide,</l>
                  <l>To purge his Children, from the ſin of Pride.</l>
                  <l>By Gods Chaſtiſements, man is often brought,</l>
                  <l>To true Repentance, which thereby is taught.</l>
                  <l>Repentance, is the pretious fruit that growes,</l>
                  <l>Upon the Croſs, this Thorne doth beare a Roſe.</l>
                  <l>Afflictions do Gods children truly trie,</l>
                  <l>They are the touchſtone of ſincerity.</l>
                  <l>They make them zealons when they pray to God,</l>
                  <l>They are moſt fervent? when they feel the Rod.</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49076:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ionah,</hi> ſecurely, in the ſhip did ſleep,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Ionah</hi> prayd, in danger, in the deep,</l>
                  <l>Affliction ſifts the ſoul of ſinful man,</l>
                  <l>It tries his Faith, 'tis Gods refining Fan.</l>
                  <l>Faith propt with Patience, bears the greateſt weight</l>
                  <l>This far ſhines brighteſt, in the darkeſt night.</l>
                  <l>Tis God that doth our Graces often trie,</l>
                  <l>Submit to him, much comfort comes thereby.</l>
                  <l>Do not withſtand Gods way, which works out ſin;</l>
                  <l>Thy heart's impure, much droſs is found therein.</l>
                  <l>By Gods chaſtiſements, man receives no loſs,</l>
                  <l>This fiery furnace, purgeth out the droſs,</l>
                  <l>Tho <hi>Shadrach, Meſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were in the Furnace hot; they felt no woe.</l>
                  <l>They were faſt bound, and caſt into the fire,</l>
                  <l>It burnt their bonds, it burnt not their attire.</l>
                  <l>So doth the fire of our Afflictions trie,</l>
                  <l>And burns the bonds of our iniquity.</l>
                  <l>We are Gods people, and his husbandry,</l>
                  <l>Within our hearts, the ſeeds of ſin do lye,</l>
                  <l>He Ploughs them up, deſtroyes the wicked weed,</l>
                  <l>And in our hearts, he ſowes a holy ſeed.</l>
                  <l>He kills the Tares, he Harrowes every part,</l>
                  <l>Afflictions help, to make a holy heart.</l>
                  <l>True Faith put forth, moſt pure and noble acts,</l>
                  <l>In times of tryal, faith beats fearing back.</l>
                  <l>The Torch that's beaten, gives the greater light,</l>
                  <l>Faith in affliction, ſhineth far more bright.</l>
                  <l>The Bay, and Cipreſs, flouriſh in the ſhade,</l>
                  <l>But in the Sun, theſe fragrant flowers fade,</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49076:10"/>
                  <l>The ſhade of ſorrow, more improves thy Grace,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhining ſolace, in a pleaſant Place.</l>
                  <l>Then murmur not, ſubmit to God moſt high,</l>
                  <l>Accept that well, which makes thee fructifie.</l>
                  <l>By diſcontent, our Prayers we do confute,</l>
                  <l>We pray (thy will be don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,) this is our ſuite.</l>
                  <l>And yet we murmur in Adverſity,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhewes our Prayers, are in Hipocryſy.</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou more ſorrow, then ſome others have,</l>
                  <l>Then ſeek to God, and his aſſiſtance crave.</l>
                  <l>He can ſupport thee in thy ſorrowes all,</l>
                  <l>And ſet thee free, from all thy Bonds and thrall.</l>
                  <l>The Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> was by wicked men,</l>
                  <l>Accus'd and caſt, into the Lyons Den.</l>
                  <l>Yet was preſerv'd by Gods Almighty power,</l>
                  <l>The hungry Lions, did not him devoure.</l>
                  <l>But his accuſers, found them violent,</l>
                  <l>Their bones they brake, God ſav'd the innocent.</l>
                  <l>Great ſufferings are, the way to glory great,</l>
                  <l>God's bleſſed Son, did blood and water ſweat.</l>
                  <l>He ſuffered death, and yet was free from ſin,</l>
                  <l>He payd thy debt, wilt thou do nought for him?</l>
                  <l>O be content, do not thy caſe condole,</l>
                  <l>Afflictions help, to cure a ſin ſick ſoule.</l>
                  <l>But male content, of grief, and anger both,</l>
                  <l>A mixture hath, and raiſeth ſtormy wroth.</l>
                  <l>Within thy ſoul this ſpirit reſtleſs is,</l>
                  <l>Tis never quiet, ſomething is amiſs.</l>
                  <l>The mans not ſick, and yet he's never well,</l>
                  <l>Aske what he ailes; alas he cannot tell.</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49076:10"/>
                  <l>What is the matter? his great diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Hath diſcompos'd his heart, and made a rent.</l>
                  <l>There is no ſtate can pleaſe his wavering mind,</l>
                  <l>In no condition, he can comfort find.</l>
                  <l>He runs the round, he ends where he begun,</l>
                  <l>Moves to and fro, diſlikes both ſhade and ſun.</l>
                  <l>Faith looks beyond, the help of earthly things,</l>
                  <l>And feeds upon, both hope, and promiſings</l>
                  <l>Faith will truſt God, where him it cannot trace,</l>
                  <l>And will adventure of his word, and grace.</l>
                  <l>But diſcontent, no reaſon will obey,</l>
                  <l>The rules of faith, it wholly caſts away.</l>
                  <l>Great ſinfulneſs, is found in diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Both in the cauſes, and the conſequent.</l>
                  <l>Pride, Envy, Avatice, and Unbeleif,</l>
                  <l>Of diſcontent, theſe are the cauſes chief.</l>
                  <l>Pride makes a man, too highly to eſteem,</l>
                  <l>His own deſerts, and others meanly deem.</l>
                  <l>His own condition, he conceives too low,</l>
                  <l>And ſo blames God, becauſe he made it ſo.</l>
                  <l>And this proud man, preſume to tax the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he plac'd him in no higher Orb.</l>
                  <l>So Envy is, a very divelliſh ſin,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> was holy, Satan envyed him.</l>
                  <l>The ſacrifice of <hi>Abel,</hi> was accepted,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> envyed him, becauſe (his) was rejected</l>
                  <l>And Avarice, doth cauſe great diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Tis ever craveing, alwaies indigent.</l>
                  <l>For Covetouſneſs, contentedneſs, doth thwart,</l>
                  <l>They cannot both, live in a holy heart.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49076:11"/>
                  <l>Diſtruſt's an evil, greater then diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>'Tis inconſiſtent with contentedneſs.</l>
                  <l>And diſcontent, it is a dayly grief,</l>
                  <l>It is the Eccho, of mans unbeleif.</l>
                  <l>And this diſtemper, cauſeth ſuch diſcord,</l>
                  <l>That man with gladneſs, cannot ſerve the Lord,</l>
                  <l>For diſcontent doth alwaies live in want,</l>
                  <l>Unthankfulneſs is its concomitant.</l>
                  <l>This diſcontent, made <hi>Ahab, Naboth</hi> ſtone,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, might be come his own.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Abſolom</hi> it caus'd to ſeek a Crown,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe himſelf, and pull his Father down.</l>
                  <l>This diſcontent doth dayly ſtir up ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>It takes away the comfort of mans life.</l>
                  <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man hath much, and yet do thirſt for more,</l>
                  <l>He's diſcontent, this makes the Rich man poor.</l>
                  <l>We nought deſerve, and yet we much deſire</l>
                  <l>If God deny us, we are full of ire.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Ionahs</hi> Guard, (that withering vanity)</l>
                  <l>Was ſmitten, <hi>Ionah</hi> in a Pet would die.</l>
                  <l>All live in want, that live in diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Rich men are rob'd, by this diſtemperment.</l>
                  <l>Through diſcontent, ſome murmur, ſome do mourn</l>
                  <l>Which maketh God, their mercies to adjourn.</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou have mercy, ſeek to God and pray;</l>
                  <l>This murmuring doth God's mercy much delay.</l>
                  <l>When children ſtruggle, they are beaten worſe,</l>
                  <l>Our ſinful paſſions, cauſe a heavy curſe.</l>
                  <l>The Iſralites, by murmuring diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Procur'd from God, a heavy puniſhment.</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49076:11"/>
                  <l>They were rewarded, for their peeviſhneſs,</l>
                  <l>They wandred long, within the wilderneſs.</l>
                  <l>Then ſtrive (O man) againſt thy diſcontent.</l>
                  <l>This evil ſpirit labour to prevent.</l>
                  <l>The world is ſuch, that men the more they have,</l>
                  <l>Are leſs content, which makes them more to crave</l>
                  <l>Doth Wealth increaſe? the worldly mans deſire</l>
                  <l>Increaſeth more; this Oyle inflames the fire.</l>
                  <l>The heart of man triangular is found,</l>
                  <l>The world is very Circular and Round.</l>
                  <l>There is nothing, man's ſoul can ſatisfie,</l>
                  <l>But God, the Lord, the Holy Trinity.</l>
                  <l>Then covet not much wealth, ſtrive for content</l>
                  <l>Life is a vapour, and is quickly ſpent.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes the Sun goes down<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before noon day,</l>
                  <l>Before old age, grim death, takes life away.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes the Sun of life, ſets preſently,</l>
                  <l>Death doth approach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the dawning Infancy.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes it is Eclipſed in the Womb,</l>
                  <l>The mothers belly doth the babe intombe.</l>
                  <l>Man's here to day, to morrow he is gone,</l>
                  <l>Our winged Time, goes very ſwiftly on,</l>
                  <l>Life is uncertain, long it cannot laſt,</l>
                  <l>It is a wheel, that's running ever faſt.</l>
                  <l>Man's life it is, compared to a day,</l>
                  <l>Or to a Poſt, that rideth faſt away.</l>
                  <l>Our life is ſhort, long here we cannot ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And little will, our charges here defray.</l>
                  <l>It is not far, unto our journeys end,</l>
                  <l>And after death, we need no more to ſpend.</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49076:12"/>
                  <l>If Farmers ſhould, great ſummes of money ſpend,</l>
                  <l>In Building; when their terme is neer an end,</l>
                  <l>They would be deemed very indiſcreet,</l>
                  <l>For building where, they have no better right.</l>
                  <l>So he that doth, immoderately give,</l>
                  <l>His mind to Wealth; and hath ſhort time to live.</l>
                  <l>May be accounted, for a carnal man,</l>
                  <l>That ſlights his ſoul, he is no Chriſtian.</l>
                  <l>Then learn content, for wealth cannot delay,</l>
                  <l>The Pangs of Death, which take thy life away.</l>
                  <l>Sad thoughts and troubles, often here attend,</l>
                  <l>A great Eſtate, and terrour in the end.</l>
                  <l>Tis not aboundance, that a man enjoyes,</l>
                  <l>That is the thing, wherein contentment lies,</l>
                  <l>An evil ſpirit, haunts the Worldlings Cheſt,</l>
                  <l>So that the Miſer, cannot be at reſt,</l>
                  <l>His heaps of Gold, he ſtrives to hide them ſure,</l>
                  <l>He takes great care, his Riches to ſecure.</l>
                  <l>His worldly wealth, he labours to increaſe,</l>
                  <l>His anxious thoughts, deſtroy his inward peace.</l>
                  <l>The World affordeth many pleaſant things,</l>
                  <l>This Bee, gives Honey, but it often ſtings.</l>
                  <l>Within the Sunſhine, is the pleaſant ſeat,</l>
                  <l>Yet it is troubled, with the ſcotching heat.</l>
                  <l>Moſt men they do, delight in dainty fare,</l>
                  <l>The Rich mans table, often is his ſnare,</l>
                  <l>He quickly may, ingulf himſelf too deep,</l>
                  <l>And drowned be, within theſe waters ſweet.</l>
                  <l>Tis difficult, to know how to abound,</l>
                  <l>Good Salve ill us'd, may make a greater wound.</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49076:12"/>
                  <l>So many times, mans great Proſperity,</l>
                  <l>Doth make him Proud and cauſe ſecurity.</l>
                  <l>And yet aboundance, few mens hearts doth fill,</l>
                  <l>But many ſouls this Pluriſy doth kill.</l>
                  <l>Then with a little learn to be content,</l>
                  <l>Srive to be good, not to be eminent.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Iacob,</hi> for his Pillow had a ſtone,</l>
                  <l>And when his body, lay the earth upon,</l>
                  <l>He ſweetly ſlept, and did enjoy his reſt,</l>
                  <l>For Food and Rayment, <hi>Iacob</hi> made requeſt.</l>
                  <l>Doth wealth increaſe? it doth increaſe thy cares,</l>
                  <l>And may thee draw, into a world of ſnares,</l>
                  <l>Small Pinaces, ride ſafe upon the Sea,</l>
                  <l>When ſtorms, and winds caſt gallant Ships away.</l>
                  <l>Our Father <hi>Adam</hi> fell in Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> from the Dunghil, had a glorious riſe.</l>
                  <l>Strong <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſlept, ſecurely on the lap,</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Dalilah,</hi> that ſought his life to trap.</l>
                  <l>The fawning world, is worſe then when it frownes,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt cares, attend the Richeſt Crownes.</l>
                  <l>When men grow rich, their hearts begin to ſwell,</l>
                  <l>The ſin of Pride, in rich mens hearts doth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ll.</l>
                  <l>Obſerve how mad men, when the Moon declines</l>
                  <l>Are quieter; then, when it's in the prime.</l>
                  <l>When mens Eſtates, are low, and in the Waine,</l>
                  <l>They humble are, and leſs mind worldly gain.</l>
                  <l>Then be contented, with thy preſent lott,</l>
                  <l>If thou have leſs then others, envy not.</l>
                  <l>A great Eſtate, great envy to it drawes,</l>
                  <l>Men hate Superiours, that's the greateſt cauſe.</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49076:13"/>
                  <l>When <hi>David</hi> kept, his Father <hi>Ieſſe's</hi> ſheep,</l>
                  <l>None did him envy, none his life did ſeek,</l>
                  <l>But when he did, enjoy a Kingly Crown,</l>
                  <l>Then envy ſought, to bring his Honour down.</l>
                  <l>An envious man; he hath an evil Eye,</l>
                  <l>He hates to ſee, good mens Proſperity.</l>
                  <l>Then be content, ſeek not too high to mount,</l>
                  <l>The more thou haſt; the greater's thy account.</l>
                  <l>Trade for Gods Glory, haſt thou leſs or more,</l>
                  <l>Lay out thy money, on this publick ſcore,</l>
                  <l>Caſt in thy Mite, into this Treaſury,</l>
                  <l>Improve thy Talent, for Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Art thou exalted, to a high degree?</l>
                  <l>Then in good Works, (man) labour Rich to be,</l>
                  <l>Remember that, thou art a Steward here,</l>
                  <l>Prepare thy ſelf, and make thy reckoning cleare.</l>
                  <l>Againſt thy Lord, and Maſter, call for it,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt account, for this thy Stewardſhip.</l>
                  <l>And when this great account, is clearely paſt,</l>
                  <l>Then thou art free, this reckoning is thy laſt.</l>
                  <l>Then what if thou, ſome hardſhip here indure?</l>
                  <l>Death ends thy Hell, and then thy Heaven's ſure.</l>
                  <l>Rich <hi>Dives</hi> did, poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> diſdain,</l>
                  <l>Who craved crumbs, his life for to ſuſtein,</l>
                  <l>And yet the doggs, ſome pitty took on him,</l>
                  <l>As if thoſe doggs; had his Phyſitians been.</l>
                  <l>They lickt his ſores, when <hi>Lazarus</hi> did lie,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Dives</hi> gate, to beg his Charity.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Lazarus</hi> he, from ſorrow ſoon was quit,</l>
                  <l>Here was his Hell, he was releaſt from it.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49076:13"/>
                  <l>And was by Angels, carried clear away,</l>
                  <l>To Paradiſe, where he ſhall be for aye.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Dives</hi> was, ſent to the loweſt Hell,</l>
                  <l>Where he with Divels ſhall for ever dwell,</l>
                  <l>And in his torments, in the flaming fire,</l>
                  <l>A little water, <hi>Dives</hi> did deſire.</l>
                  <l>To cool it tongue, but could it not obtain,</l>
                  <l>The damned muſt, endure eternal pain.</l>
                  <l>He that would not, afford the poor a crumb,</l>
                  <l>For water cryd; to cool his burning tounge,</l>
                  <l>Obſerve Gods Juſtice upon wicked men,</l>
                  <l>That have no mercy; he hath none for them.</l>
                  <l>And ſeek by prayer, Gods Judgements to prevent,</l>
                  <l>Uſe well thy wealth, and learn to be content.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is a judgement, for a man to have,</l>
                  <l>A great Eſtate; and yet ſtill more to crave.</l>
                  <l>The greedy man will never be content,</l>
                  <l>He cryes give, give, he's alwaies indigent.</l>
                  <l>He eats, and drinks, and yet's not ſatisfi'd,</l>
                  <l>This glutton hath, a greedy appetite.</l>
                  <l>For avarice, doth foſter diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, is a ſin, it is a puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>It is accounted for a ſecret curſe,</l>
                  <l>For goods ill gotten, makes the gainers worſe.</l>
                  <l>The more they have, the leſs they are content,</l>
                  <l>The more they crave, the more's their puniſhment</l>
                  <l>For heaps of ſilver, cannot ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Him that loves ſilver, here's his miſery.</l>
                  <l>Then ſtrive for grace, and greatneſs ſet aſide,</l>
                  <l>Be not content, till ſin be mortifi'd.</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49076:14"/>
                  <l>Though ſin, in the regenerate remain</l>
                  <l>Yet ſin in them, doth never rule not reign,</l>
                  <l>Be not contented, with thy natural ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Gods Wrath purſues, the Unregenerate.</l>
                  <l>And how canſt thou, indure his wrathful ire?</l>
                  <l>Or who dwell with everlaſting fire?</l>
                  <l>A natural man, is under Satans power,</l>
                  <l>This roaring Lion, ſeeketh to devóure.</l>
                  <l>Be not contented, with thy wicked ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Get true Repentance, ere it be too late.</l>
                  <l>He thats indebted, till the debt be paid,</l>
                  <l>May be Arreſted, and in Priſon laid.</l>
                  <l>Thou art indebted; man by <hi>Adam</hi> fell,</l>
                  <l>Thou mayſt be carried<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Priſoner unto Hell.</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not pay, who will thy ſurety be,</l>
                  <l>There's none but Chriſt, can undertake for thee.</l>
                  <l>O then Repent, lay hold on Chriſt by Faith,</l>
                  <l>O be contented, thou art under wrath.</l>
                  <l>Change thy condition, haſten out ſin,</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt be damned, if thou die therein.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lott Sodome</hi> quit, that City full of ſin,</l>
                  <l>Was all deſtroy'd, and all that ſtayd therein.</l>
                  <l>The longer man, continues in his ſin</l>
                  <l>The ſtronger hold, doth Satan get in him.</l>
                  <l>A Gartiſon that's ſtrongly fortifi'd,</l>
                  <l>And victuall'd well, ſoon cannot be deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>A Plant that's young, ſoon plucked up may be,</l>
                  <l>But thou canſt not, pluck up a rooted tree.</l>
                  <l>If thou be rooted in the ſin of Pride,</l>
                  <l>And unbeleif, and nature, be thy guide,</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49076:14"/>
                  <l>Tis hard to pluck up, thoſe great roots of ſin,</l>
                  <l>Which all thy life, thou haſt been rooted in.</l>
                  <l>Break off thy ſins and chooſe the better part,</l>
                  <l>O man Repent, and get a broken heart,</l>
                  <l>Thou better hadſt, abide the grief and pain,</l>
                  <l>Of ſetting bones, then all thy life be lame.</l>
                  <l>That trouble's bleſt, that brings the ſoul to God,</l>
                  <l>With patience beare, the Lords chaſtiſing Rod.</l>
                  <l>A Conſcience bad, and quiet; needs muſt be,</l>
                  <l>An evil ſtate, a ſinful Lichargy.</l>
                  <l>Let no condition, that diſhonour brings,</l>
                  <l>Unto the Lord, who is the King of Kings.</l>
                  <l>Give thee content, therein's no inward peace,</l>
                  <l>And outward comforts, they will ſhortly ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>Take heed of trading, in a courſe of ſin,</l>
                  <l>God never call'd thee, for to trade therein,</l>
                  <l>Art thou a ſervant? labour ſpeedily,</l>
                  <l>To get into ſome godly Family.</l>
                  <l>Continue not, be not content to dwell,</l>
                  <l>Within the Suburbs, or the ſmoak of Hell.</l>
                  <l>But haſten out, of wicked ſinners tents,</l>
                  <l>Leſt thou incurr their heavy puniſhments.</l>
                  <l>Or be infected, with the Poyſoning ſin,</l>
                  <l>Of ill example that abounds therein.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Ioſeph</hi> liv'd, and greateſt ſway did beare,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pharohs</hi> Court, he learned there to ſwear.</l>
                  <l>An ill example, ſoon is ſucked in,</l>
                  <l>Our eyes behold, our eares do let in ſin,</l>
                  <l>Good men by bad, may ſooner be perverted,</l>
                  <l>Then bad by good, to godlineſs converted.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49076:15"/>
                  <l>A maſter bad, a ſervant bad doth make,</l>
                  <l>Men by their Maſters, do example take.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Labans</hi> flock, the pilled rods did ſee,</l>
                  <l>Of Poplar, Haſle, and the Cheſnut tree,</l>
                  <l>They did conceive and brought forth ſpeckle Goa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>With white, Ring-ſtraked, and with ſpotted coate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men quickly learn, the tune that others ſing,</l>
                  <l>Examples draw, and are prevailing things.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Kedars</hi> tents, then do not thou reſide,</l>
                  <l>Leſt with the wicked, thou ſhouldſt be deſtroyd.</l>
                  <l>If in a wicked Family thou dwell,</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt inhabit in a little Hell.</l>
                  <l>A good mans houſe with bleſſing is perfum'd,</l>
                  <l>The evil mans, in wrath ſhall be conſum'd.</l>
                  <l>When on the head, the holy Oyle of Grace,</l>
                  <l>Is poured out, it much perfumes the place.</l>
                  <l>And doth diffuſe it ſelf, moſt pleaſantly,</l>
                  <l>Upon the skirts, of all the family.</l>
                  <l>Then labour thou, to live in ſuch a place,</l>
                  <l>Where (by Gods bleſſing) thou maiſt get more Grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>For good examples, are magnetical</l>
                  <l>But ill examples, do in danger all.</l>
                  <l>Be not contented, with a little grace,</l>
                  <l>But ſtrive for more, be growing up apace.</l>
                  <l>Tis not enough, that thou have only life,</l>
                  <l>Grace is increaſed, by a holy ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> preſſed hard, towards the Holy place,</l>
                  <l>Still ſtriving for, a greater ſtock of grace.</l>
                  <l>Some Stars in brightneſs, others do tranſcend,</l>
                  <l>More Grace, more Glory, bringeth in the end</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49076:15"/>
                  <l>Then ſtrive for Grace, but ſeek not for content</l>
                  <l>In worldly wealth, which is not permanent.</l>
                  <l>Let Holineſs, then be thy hearts delight,</l>
                  <l>Of Holineſs God is the Prototype.</l>
                  <l>He is the Pattern and Original,</l>
                  <l>Of Holineſs; but we are ſinners all.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Divine Contentment,</hi> is a happy thing,</l>
                  <l>From this ſweet Root doth conſolation ſpring.</l>
                  <l>Contented Spirits, chearful ſpirits are,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Golden Shields, keep off diſtracting care,</l>
                  <l>A cheerful Chriſtian, will himſelf ſubmit,</l>
                  <l>Unto Gods dealings, and rejoyce in it.</l>
                  <l>The inward joy of him, doth not abate,</l>
                  <l>That is contented, with his preſent ſtate.</l>
                  <l>He that's contented, hath a thankful heart,</l>
                  <l>And all Afflictions taketh in good part,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Contemplations, holy hearts do raiſe,</l>
                  <l>They ſtrive to be, the patterns of God's praiſe.</l>
                  <l>To the contented nothing comes amiſs;</l>
                  <l>In all conditions, he contented is.</l>
                  <l>Contented Chriſtians, they are only thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who wholly do, ſubmit to Gods diſpoſe.</l>
                  <l>And will not run into a courſe of ſin,</l>
                  <l>To rid themſelves, from troubles they are in.</l>
                  <l>But are contented, willingly to wait,</l>
                  <l>Gods leiſure; till he free them from their ſtreight.</l>
                  <l>Diſquietneſs, proceeds from unbeleif,</l>
                  <l>This want of Faith, doth cauſe this inward grief.</l>
                  <l>Faith ſcatters fears, and doubtings puts to flight,</l>
                  <l>It ſtills the heart when paſſions would affright,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49076:16"/>
                  <l>Faith chides down paſſion, and prevents that ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>When reaſon ſinckes, then Faith aloft doth ſwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Faith ſhewes the ſoul, that all its tryals are,</l>
                  <l>From God in love; who of the ſoul takes care,</l>
                  <l>Then humble be, and learn to be content,</l>
                  <l>If Croſſes come, be not impatient.</l>
                  <l>Keep Conſcience clear, indulge not any ſin,</l>
                  <l>Guilt breeds diſquiet, if it be therein.</l>
                  <l>When as the More is got into the eye,</l>
                  <l>It makes it ſore, it makes it watery.</l>
                  <l>And ſo doth ſin, raiſe tempeſts in the ſoul,</l>
                  <l>And brings a curſe, it brings a flying roule.</l>
                  <l>But if thou keep the eye of conſcience clear,</l>
                  <l>This flying roule, can never enter there.</l>
                  <l>Then pray to God, invoke his holy name,</l>
                  <l>O get thy heart into a praying frame.</l>
                  <l>Prayer will prevail, againſt thy diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>In greateſt grief, Prayer gives a holy vent,</l>
                  <l>The Key of Prayer, well oyl'd with bryny tears</l>
                  <l>Unlocks the heart, of its affrighting fears.</l>
                  <l>By Prayer to God, unboſome then thy ſoul,</l>
                  <l>And eke thy ſelf, upon thy Saviour roul.</l>
                  <l>Make known thy mind, unto thy faithful friend,</l>
                  <l>Who to thy heart, can eaſe and quiet ſend.</l>
                  <l>Unload thy ſoul, into thy Saviours breſt,</l>
                  <l>Where it may have, all ſweet content and reſt.</l>
                  <l>Though (God) and (man) and both, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Give true contentment to <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:16"/>
               </div>
               <div type="poems">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:17"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49076:17"/>
                  <head>Poems of Praiſe, and Poems upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Subjects.</head>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <l>GOod <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> pleaſant Poems ſings,</l>
                     <l>To God the Lord, the only King of Kings,</l>
                     <l>Who heard his Prayers, and granted his requeſt,</l>
                     <l>Who heald his Plague, and freed him from the Peſt</l>
                     <l>A good example, from a godly King,</l>
                     <l>The godly ones; God's Praiſes ought to ſing.</l>
                     <l>When they are cumbered, with the greateſt fear,</l>
                     <l>Terrors, and troubles, of their Conſcience: where</l>
                     <l>Can they have help, but from their gracious God</l>
                     <l>Who whips his Children, after burns the rod.</l>
                     <l>Both Rich and Poor, then pay your chief age to</l>
                     <l>The Lord of Lords, the Rent of Praiſe you owe.</l>
                     <l>Can you pay leſs, unto ſo good a Lord,</l>
                     <l>Who gave his only Son, his Holy Word,</l>
                     <l>To ſave his Saints, to free their Souls from pain</l>
                     <l>To die for them, that they might live again.</l>
                     <l>Who all were dead, by <hi>Adams</hi> ſinful fall,</l>
                     <l>But now revived, by Chriſt's Funeral.</l>
                     <l>Who all were ſlaves, till Jeſus made them free,</l>
                     <l>Till Chriſt did die, and climb the curſed Tree.</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49076:18"/>
                     <l>Praiſe God, praiſe God, praiſe God the Lord on high</l>
                     <l>Praiſe God the Lord; the Holy Trinity.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt hath redeem'd thee, and diſcharg'd thy ſcor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Praiſe God the Lord, praiſe him for evermore.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Proverbs, Chap. 18. Ver. 14.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <l>Mans ſpirit, will, Infirmities ſuſtein,</l>
                           <l>But who can beare, the woundea ſpirits pain.</l>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MAns ſpirit that, is furniſhed with Grace,</l>
                        <l>And fortifi'd with favour of God's Face</l>
                        <l>May paſs the Pikes, and Conquer all his foes,</l>
                        <l>Why ſhould he fear, when God keeps back th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> blowe</l>
                        <l>If God be for us, who can us withſtand?</l>
                        <l>Who can oppoſe <hi>Iehovah's</hi> mighty hand?</l>
                        <l>Whoſe mercy to his people, hath no bounds,</l>
                        <l>Nor ſtint, nor limit, it is ſo profound.</l>
                        <l>Th' impetuous current, of the rageing Sea,</l>
                        <l>He made Recoyle, to make his people way.</l>
                        <l>He made the flames, of hot and burning fire,</l>
                        <l>From his three Children, ſwiftly to retire.</l>
                        <l>He made the Roaring Lyons, couch and quake,</l>
                        <l>And change their natures, for his <hi>Daniels</hi> ſake.</l>
                        <l>He made the Locuſts, lice, and Froggs and Flies,</l>
                        <l>In battel ray, at his command to riſe:</l>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49076:18"/>
                        <l>To ſave his people, from their cruel foes,</l>
                        <l>To curb proud <hi>Pharoh,</hi> that did them oppoſe.</l>
                        <l>He fed <hi>Elijah</hi> by the croking Crow,</l>
                        <l>When <hi>Iezebel,</hi> did ſeek his overthrow.</l>
                        <l>He made the Furnace, like a downy bed,</l>
                        <l>To bleſſed <hi>Bainham,</hi> that was Martyred.</l>
                        <l>When <hi>David</hi> hunted was, by wicked <hi>Saul,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments 1030</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>When robbed of his wives, and children all,</l>
                        <l>When <hi>Zigglag</hi> was, to aſhes burnt with fire,</l>
                        <l>When <hi>David</hi> had, no place of ſafe retire.</l>
                        <l>When <hi>David's</hi> Souldiers, ſpake of ſcorning him,</l>
                        <l>When Holy <hi>David</hi> was great troubles in.</l>
                        <l>Then in diſtreſs, poor <hi>David</hi> wept full ſore,</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>David</hi> wept, till he could weep no more,</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>David</hi> did, unto <hi>Iehovah</hi> crie</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>David</hi> prayd, to God in miſery.</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>David's</hi> courage, was (by God) ſtir'd up,</l>
                        <l>Then to the ſword, th' <hi>Amalekites</hi> he put.</l>
                        <l>Then by the ſword, he made his enemies fall,</l>
                        <l>Then by Gods help he did recover all.</l>
                        <l>Then all true Saints: take courage in the Lord,</l>
                        <l>Truſt him in trouble, read his Holy Word.</l>
                        <l>By weak; without; againſt means; he can free</l>
                        <l>His Saints and Servants, from their miſery.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sith a good Conſcience and a ſtock of grace</l>
                        <l>Be'th only means t'incounter and out face,<note place="margin">Poems. of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Our grand oppoſer, and to draw the ſtings</l>
                        <l>Out of our ſorrowes, and our ſufferings,</l>
                        <l>And in the dreadful day, ſo ſoveraign are,</l>
                        <l>To ſave the ſoul from ſinking in deſpair.</l>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49076:19"/>
                        <l>Then be reproved, thoſe that take no care,</l>
                        <l>But are ſecure and ſleight theſe Jewels rare.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe Fools and Bedlams, that have ſuch a price</l>
                        <l>Put in their hands, and yet are not ſo wiſe</l>
                        <l>It to improve, for their eternal bliſs,</l>
                        <l>But all their life, and health imployed is.</l>
                        <l>In ſenſual luſts, and on their Dunghil pleaſures,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt they neglect, rich and eternal treaſures.</l>
                        <l>What do you think, to ſuch poor ſouls belongs,</l>
                        <l>That pleaſure take, in Satans Syren ſongs?</l>
                        <l>And drink themſelves drunk, with Proſperity,</l>
                        <l>And take no care about Eternity.</l>
                        <l>But ſwiming down, the current of the times,</l>
                        <l>Neglect Gods grace, and graſp at Golden Mines.</l>
                        <l>Abuſe, miſuſe, unthankfully miſpend,</l>
                        <l>Their time and Talents, to an evil end.</l>
                        <l>Neglect the Harveſt time, of ining grace,</l>
                        <l>And all their lives, licentious tracks do trace,</l>
                        <l>For wealth and riches, run, and ride, and ſtrive,</l>
                        <l>And ſayl a pace, at Honour to arrive.</l>
                        <l>Alas poor ſouls, they ſeek to bear great ſway,</l>
                        <l>But will that help them in the evil day?</l>
                        <l>When the hot gleam of earthly glory's paſt,</l>
                        <l>Great Clouds of diſmal darkneſs draw on faſt,</l>
                        <l>The griſly King of terrours ſtops their breath,</l>
                        <l>And they are haled to the port of death.</l>
                        <l>Then fiery flames, ſhall make them fear and quake</l>
                        <l>They muſt be drowned, in the burning lake.</l>
                        <l>What will theſe ſleepers in the Harveſt ſay,</l>
                        <l>When they be waked at the dreadful day?</l>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49076:19"/>
                        <l>When guilty conſcience, gnawing at the heart,</l>
                        <l>Like to a Vulture, fiercely plaies his part,</l>
                        <l>What will become of all the wicked then?</l>
                        <l>What is portion of ſuch wicked men?</l>
                        <l>O vile ungrateful wretch, then hide thy face,</l>
                        <l>God did capacitate thy ſoul, for grace,</l>
                        <l>Why then doſt thou ſo lull thy ſelf in luſt,</l>
                        <l>Self love and Pride, are not God's Judgements juſt?</l>
                        <l>Waſt made for naught, but drink, and ſleep, &amp; eate?</l>
                        <l>Laugh and be merry, that's a vain conceit.</l>
                        <l>Is Conſcience ſeard? then ther's no more to ſay,</l>
                        <l>But to adjourn thee, to the dreadful day.</l>
                        <l>But yet I pray, thou maiſt reform thy waies,</l>
                        <l>Redeem the time, the remainder of thy daies.</l>
                        <l>Awake, awake, and ſtrike upon thy thigh,</l>
                        <l>Wraſtle with God, by ſervent Prayer and crye.</l>
                        <l>Faith and Repentance is the onely way,</l>
                        <l>Againſt deſpairing in the evil day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Of all bad men,<note place="margin">Of the ſaving Light.</note> moſt peſtilent are thoſe,</l>
                        <l>That impiouſly, God's Miniſtry oppoſe,</l>
                        <l>And by their hatred, malice and deſpight,</l>
                        <l>Study and ſtrive to quench the ſaving light.</l>
                        <l>All that oppoſe, the ſaving word of grace,</l>
                        <l>Do ſtrike directly, at Chriſt's bleſſed face,</l>
                        <l>Who is as tender, of his Miniſtry,</l>
                        <l>As he is of the Aple of his Eye.</l>
                        <l>O then Repent, to God make thine addreſs,</l>
                        <l>Wound not thy Conſcience, with ſuch wickedneſs.</l>
                        <l>The ſin of Perſecution lowdly cries,</l>
                        <l>At Gods Tribunal, makes a hideous noiſe.</l>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49076:20"/>
                        <l>For juſt revenge, the vengeance of Gods ire</l>
                        <l>For tempeſts great, for ſhowres of flaming fire.</l>
                        <l>To be diſtill'd, and poured down on them,</l>
                        <l>That are ſuch cruel, and blood thirſty men.</l>
                        <l>How long O Lord? O holy juſt and true,</l>
                        <l>Avenge our blood, pay wicked men their due,</l>
                        <l>Theſe ſpightful ſpirits heated with hell fire,</l>
                        <l>Fleſht with the blood of Saints, do much deſire.</l>
                        <l>To cloud the Sun, the Goſpel of Gods Grace,</l>
                        <l>In which tranſparent glaſs, Saints ſee his face.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>The Nature of a Wounded Spirit.</head>
                     <l>FRom wounded ſpirits, there ariſeth fear,</l>
                     <l>A wounded Conſcience, what proud heart can beare?</l>
                     <l>Man doth conflict in this great miſery</l>
                     <l>With God himſelf, a God of Majeſty.</l>
                     <l>Can ſinful man, contend with God moſt high?</l>
                     <l>Or duſt and aſhes, with eternity.</l>
                     <l>When God is angry, no poor ſoul can ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the fierceneſs, of his heavy hand.</l>
                     <l>Can ſtubble dry'd; repel the flaming fire,</l>
                     <l>No more can we, reſiſt <hi>Iehovah's</hi> ire.</l>
                     <l>When we are whipt, and laſhed with his rod,</l>
                     <l>And do behold the frowning face of God,</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49076:20"/>
                     <l>Then we like leaves, with wind ſoon ſhaken are,</l>
                     <l>And tertifi'd with flaſhings, of deſpair.</l>
                     <l>Our heavy hearts, for fear, both faint and faile,</l>
                     <l>Our ſilly ſouls will then our ſins bewail.</l>
                     <l>Then with our ſelves, we are at enmity,</l>
                     <l>And do inlarge the rent moſt grievouſly.</l>
                     <l>For when our ſouls, are in this trembling caſe,</l>
                     <l>We love too much, in Satan's Glaſs to gaze.</l>
                     <l>Who labours much, by lying cruelty;</l>
                     <l>Our ſins both to inlarge and multiply.</l>
                     <l>Of every Molehil, he a Mountain makes.</l>
                     <l>That wounded ſpirits, may no comfort take,</l>
                     <l>To every ſin, he adds a bloody ſting,</l>
                     <l>That he poor ſinners, to deſpair may bring.</l>
                     <l>Then what they think, remember, ſee or hear,</l>
                     <l>Is turnd to terrour, and to hideous fear.</l>
                     <l>The dreadful fancy, then doth bear its part,</l>
                     <l>By fained horrors, with the trembling heart.</l>
                     <l>Which is perplexed, with moſt grievous pain,</l>
                     <l>And reſtleſs anguiſh, doth therein remain:</l>
                     <l>And brings the Patient into ſuch a rage,</l>
                     <l>That he his preſent horrour to aſſwage,</l>
                     <l>Would rather die then live, and chooſe to dwell,</l>
                     <l>With Helliſh Furies, in the Pit of Hell,</l>
                     <l>Such are the terrours, of a troubled mind,</l>
                     <l>Bruiſed and wounded, in this woful kind.</l>
                     <l>As may appear, both by the deſperate cry</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> damn'd eternally.</l>
                     <l>As alſo by, the mournful ſad complaints,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and ſuch glorious Saints.</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49076:21"/>
                     <l>Theſe flames of horrour, how ſhall we endure?</l>
                     <l>What Balſome can, a wounded Conſcience cure?</l>
                     <l>In friends, not Phyſick, nothing's to be found,</l>
                     <l>The Blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> can only cure this wound.</l>
                     <l>Ye unconverted, be perſwaded then,</l>
                     <l>To turn to God; for unconverted men,</l>
                     <l>Though they awhile, in pleaſant places dwell</l>
                     <l>They'l be tranſplanted, in the Pit of Hell.</l>
                     <l>Then tis too late, Repentance then is paſt,</l>
                     <l>Redeem the time; whilſt thy ſhort life doth laſt.</l>
                     <l>Forſake not mercy, but thy ſins forſake,</l>
                     <l>God freely offers Chriſt; his offer take.</l>
                     <l>If thou refuſe, how wilt thou then avoid</l>
                     <l>The wrath of God which wicked men abide?</l>
                     <l>Art ſick, and ſenceleſs; doſt thou feel no ſmart?</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt the ſymptom of a ſtony heart.</l>
                     <l>When Conſcience ſtings, and ſins in Battail ray,</l>
                     <l>Do ſet themſelves then (in the evil day)</l>
                     <l>What wilt thou do? thoſe Lions then will tear,</l>
                     <l>Thy trembling heart and thee, confound with feare.</l>
                     <l>Then ſubtil Satan, he will play his part,</l>
                     <l>And ſhoot tentations, at thy fainting heart.</l>
                     <l>He was thy Maſter, thou diſt him obey,</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt walk with him, in the damned way.</l>
                     <l>Now in thy ſickneſs, thou wouldſt him forſake,</l>
                     <l>But now the Devil doth advantage take:</l>
                     <l>And doth indite thee, for thy evil acts,</l>
                     <l>And now thy Conſcience, proves thy filthy facts.</l>
                     <l>Thou tookſt ful draught, of carnal peace and pleaſure</l>
                     <l>Thou diſt carrouſe, &amp; tipple in great meaſure,</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49076:21"/>
                     <l>Thou didſt God's faithful Miniſters deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>And with thy tongue by ſlanders, ſcoffs and lyes.</l>
                     <l>Didſt much abuſe them, and with great deſpight,</l>
                     <l>Didſt labour much, to quench the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ving light.</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt thy will, and power, and purſe imploy,</l>
                     <l>God's faithful Saints, and ſervants to deſtroy:</l>
                     <l>Such crying ſins as theſe, and many more,</l>
                     <l>Stand on the unconverted ſinners ſcore.</l>
                     <l>Ye that are waſhed from the filth of ſin,<note place="margin">An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verted.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Free'd from that damned ſtate, your ſouls were in</l>
                     <l>Flie ſinful Luſts, defile your ſouls no more,</l>
                     <l>By ſuch Rebellion, as you did before.</l>
                     <l>Sin is moſt hateful, in the ſight of God,</l>
                     <l>And doth procure, his ſmart correcting rodd.</l>
                     <l>God loves all creatures, that he ever made,</l>
                     <l>But hateth ſin, with everlaſting hate.</l>
                     <l>Sin wounds the ſoul, brings men to miſery.</l>
                     <l>Sin was the cauſe, that God's dear Son did die,</l>
                     <l>Sin Satan made ſin ſunk him into hell,</l>
                     <l>Sin ſunk the Pit, where all the damned dwell.</l>
                     <l>Sin God offends, ſin is the greateſt evil,</l>
                     <l>Sin damns the ſoul, ſin is the rankeſt Devil.</l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> Is ſin ſo ugly? why doth moſt delight</l>
                     <l>In ſinful waies? why doth not ſin affright</l>
                     <l>Them from purſuing, of their Carnal pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>And make them ſtrive, to get eternal treaſures:</l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                        </label> Now Satan puts (on ſin) in ſuch a caſe,</l>
                     <l>A ſeeming fairneſs, on a helliſh face.</l>
                     <l>He paints this Harlott, in a handſome dreſs,</l>
                     <l>And ſouls to ſin, draws by deceitfulneſs,</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49076:22"/>
                     <l>Were this deformed Hagg, without falſe hair,</l>
                     <l>And painted face, ſhe could not ſcules inſnare.</l>
                     <l>The griſly face of ſin would men affright,</l>
                     <l>But by falſe colours it ſeems fair and bright.</l>
                     <l>Thus Satan covers, ſins deformity,</l>
                     <l>And makes it pleaſant, to the ſinners eye.</l>
                     <l>Though of it ſelf it's filthy, foul and naught,</l>
                     <l>Compar'd to meat thruſt out, into the draught.</l>
                     <l>All other filth, the body doth defile,</l>
                     <l>but ſin's contagious, and the ſoul doth ſoyle.</l>
                     <l>It's moſt infectious, like a Leproſie,</l>
                     <l>Infects the walls, the cloathes, Poſterity.</l>
                     <l>The ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> to his ſeed remains,</l>
                     <l>Till Chriſt's warm Blood, doth waſh away the ſtaines.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>The miſery of Man, not Reconciled to God in Chriſt.</head>
                     <l>O Wretched man; where ſhall my Muſe begin?</l>
                     <l>To ſtate the caſe that thy poor ſoul is in.</l>
                     <l>Who art condemned, to eternal death,</l>
                     <l>Adjudg'd to Hell, before thou draweſt breath.</l>
                     <l>Thy Father <hi>Adam,</hi> was by God created,</l>
                     <l>In innocence, in Paradiſe, was placed,</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49076:22"/>
                     <l>That he and his Poſterity might have,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mmortal life, and conquer Hell, and Grave.</l>
                     <l>To him, all earthly Creatures, were made free,</l>
                     <l>For meat and uſe, excepted was one tree,</l>
                     <l>That was forbidden, under pain of Hell,</l>
                     <l>He ate thereof, and ſo thy Father fell.</l>
                     <l>Pride puff'd him up, he did beleive the Devil,</l>
                     <l>He taſted of, the Tree of Good and Evil,</l>
                     <l>By this foul fall, eternal miſery,</l>
                     <l>Intailed was, on his Poſterity.</l>
                     <l>And made them ſubject to ſore puniſhment,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt they like thee, remain impenitent.</l>
                     <trailer>Finis <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:23"/>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49076:23"/>
                  <head>A DIVINE POEM. OR <hi>A Confeſſion of FAITH:</hi>
                  </head>
                  <byline>Compoſed in Meeter, By <hi>E. Manlove</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </byline>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Scriptures and Argments to prove them the Word of God.</head>
                     <l>BY God's good word; the way unto ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>Is truly taught, by holy Inſpiration,</l>
                     <l>O then beleive it, and the ſame obey,</l>
                     <l>Give no ſuch credit to Appocrypha:</l>
                     <l>Nor to traditions, of the Romiſh See;</l>
                     <l>All ſaving truths in Scripture written be.</l>
                     <l>And are recorded for Divinity</l>
                     <l>By truth it ſelf, the holy Trinity.</l>
                     <l>Depending not upon the teſtimony</l>
                     <l>Of any Church; the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any:</l>
                     <l>But God the Author; our moſt bleſſed Lord,</l>
                     <l>Receive them therefore, as his Holy word.</l>
                     <l>But we by witneſs, of the Church may deem,</l>
                     <l>The Scripture worthy, of a high eſteem.</l>
                     <l>O prize it highly, 'tis a pretious thing,</l>
                     <l>Sweet tidings of Salvation, it doth bring.</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:49076:24"/>
                     <l>The ſtile and doctrine, challenge reverence,</l>
                     <l>The efficacy, gives great evidence,</l>
                     <l>Of Gods known will; it makes a full diſcovery,</l>
                     <l>And ſhewes the way for ſinful man's recovery.</l>
                     <l>Though mortal man, of Scripture was the writer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet God's good ſpirit, was the ſole Inditer.</l>
                     <l>Some Secretaries, God did ſet apart,</l>
                     <l>Who ſpoke and wrote, but he inſpir'd the heart.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Writers did, for Holineſs ſurpaſs,</l>
                     <l>All Popes and Doctors, of the Romiſh Maſs.</l>
                     <l>And by their works, ſuch depth of wiſdome ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>As learned men, could not attain unto,</l>
                     <l>Yet never trained up, in Learned Schooles,</l>
                     <l>With them compar'd, Phyloſophers are fooles.</l>
                     <l>The Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> he did far ſurpaſs,</l>
                     <l>Some learned Rabbies; yet a Heardſman was.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Peter, Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> but fiſhermen,</l>
                     <l>Admired by the Elders of Jeruſalem.</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the writers, ther's a ſweet concord,</l>
                     <l>Which proves the Scripture, is the Holy Word.</l>
                     <l>None diſagree, at which we may admire,</l>
                     <l>For God (himſelf) the Penmen did inſpire,</l>
                     <l>They wrote ſuch things, as never wit could hatch</l>
                     <l>No Hiſtory, this Hiſtory doth match.</l>
                     <l>And what they wrote was full of Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>Profoundneſs, Wiſdome, and Authority:</l>
                     <l>Commanding Credit, to be had to them,</l>
                     <l>Denouncing threats, againſt all wicked men.</l>
                     <l>The end and ſcope, of all the Scriptures be,</l>
                     <l>For God's great glory, and mans felicity.</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49076:24"/>
                     <l>The writers antient, for Antiquity;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aoſes</hi> more antient, then the Heathens be.</l>
                     <l>The deadly hatred that the Divels beare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gainſt the Scriptures, (yet believe and fear)</l>
                     <l>Do prove them plainly, to proceed from God;</l>
                     <l>Nor from the dictates of meer fleſh and blood.</l>
                     <l>The preſervation of them alſo may,</l>
                     <l>(Though none in time, ſo antient be as they,)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nduce us to beleive, and eke accord,</l>
                     <l>That all the Scriptures, are God's holy word.</l>
                     <l>Experience ſhewes, the power of God in them,</l>
                     <l>Even by their humbling and exalting men.</l>
                     <l>And when God's ſpirit ſhall our hearts incline,</l>
                     <l>For to beleive theſe Miſteries ſublime,</l>
                     <l>And alſo write them, in our inward parts.</l>
                     <l>We ſhall beleive them, with beleiving hearts.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of GOD.</head>
                     <l>GOd is moſt glorious, wiſe, and doth excell,</l>
                     <l>All future things, he knowes, and can foretel:</l>
                     <l>He ſees into each corner of our hearts,</l>
                     <l>And knowes the ſecrets of our inner parts.</l>
                     <l>This great <hi>Iehovah,</hi> is Omnipotent,</l>
                     <l>Yea good and gracious, and omniſcient.</l>
                     <l>A God of love, his love, to (his) ſincere,</l>
                     <l>More then their fathers, or their mothers were.</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49076:25"/>
                     <l>He loves all things, that he did ever make,</l>
                     <l>And loves his Son, and (his) for his Sons ſake.</l>
                     <l>His mercy's great, he ſuccors (his) in need,</l>
                     <l>He did <hi>Eliſha,</hi> by the Ravens feed.</l>
                     <l>He is moſt juſt in works, in word and will,</l>
                     <l>Rewarding good, detecting what is ill.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Trinity.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GOD is one perfect Eſſence; full of Bliſs,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe being of himſelf eternal is.</l>
                        <l>Yet in this Eſſence, there are perſons three,</l>
                        <l>Diſtinct ſubſiſtances,<note place="margin">Singula ſunt in ſingulis omnia in ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula in o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibus &amp; unum omnia Aug. lib. 6. de tri. cap. ult.</note> theſe perſons be.</l>
                        <l>And yet in ſubſtance, all theſe three are one,</l>
                        <l>Gods Eſſence is, without diſtinction.</l>
                        <l>And yet the perſons, in this Eſſence be,</l>
                        <l>Diſtinguiſh'd by, the Holy Trinity.</l>
                        <l>The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt Divine,</l>
                        <l>Names, Orders, Actions do them beſt define,</l>
                        <l>The firſt the Father's named, in reſpect,</l>
                        <l>Of Chriſt his Son, and then of his Elect.</l>
                        <l>The ſecond perſon, then; the Son is nam'd,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe he's of his Fathers nature fram'd:</l>
                        <l>And of his ſubſtance, is by generation,</l>
                        <l>Th' Eternal Son of God, not by Creation.</l>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49076:25"/>
                        <l>The third, the Holy Ghoſt, who by ſpiration,</l>
                        <l>Receives his Eſſence, not by generation.</l>
                        <l>And is ſo called, both in this reſpect,</l>
                        <l>That he proceeds and ſanctifi's th' elect.</l>
                        <l>So by the order, ſeveral things we ſee,</l>
                        <l>The ſeveral workings of the Trinity.</l>
                        <l>The Father works byth' ſon, and holy ſpirit,</l>
                        <l>Yet each for dignity, of equal merit.</l>
                        <l>None firſt, none laſt ſave order, is excepted,</l>
                        <l>One God, all God, all equally reſpected.</l>
                        <l>The Glotious Eſſence; wholly in all three,</l>
                        <l>And in each perion of the Trinity.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And by the Counſel of Gods holy will,</l>
                        <l>He rul'd the world,<note place="margin">King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God his eternal decree.</note> and ſo doth rule it ſtill.</l>
                        <l>And hath determin'd all things by decree,</l>
                        <l>From time to time, from all Eternity.</l>
                        <l>Some unto life, ſome unto death there be,</l>
                        <l>Predeſtinated; by this great decree.</l>
                        <l>From hence we learn, and ſo all Chriſtians may</l>
                        <l>God deals with Duſt, as Potters do with Clay.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Creation.</head>
                     <l>GOd did of nothing, all things fitly frame,</l>
                     <l>And made them good, for Glory of his name</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49076:26"/>
                     <l>For in ſix dayes, created were by him,</l>
                     <l>The world; and all things that were made therein</l>
                     <l>And when he had all other creatures made,</l>
                     <l>Man; Male and Female, he did then create,</l>
                     <l>And into them, immortal ſouls infus'd,</l>
                     <l>With Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs indu'd.</l>
                     <l>In his own Image, he did them create,</l>
                     <l>Both free from ſin; and in a holy ſtate.</l>
                     <l>And God was pleas'd, a Covenant to frame,</l>
                     <l>And ty'd them to, performance of the ſame.</l>
                     <l>And life to them, and their poſterity,</l>
                     <l>Did promiſe, if they kept it perfectly.</l>
                     <l>They were indu'd with liberty of will,</l>
                     <l>And freedome had, his ſtatutes to fulfill.</l>
                     <l>To them all earthly Creatures, were made free,</l>
                     <l>For meat and uſe, excepted was one tree.</l>
                     <l>That was forbidden, under pain of Hell;</l>
                     <l>They are thereof;<note place="margin">The fall of man.</note> ſo Male and Female fell,</l>
                     <l>Pride puff'd them up, they did beleive the Divel,</l>
                     <l>They taſted of, the tree of good and evil.</l>
                     <l>And by this ſin, eternal miſery,</l>
                     <l>Intayled was; on their Poſterity.</l>
                     <l>Three things,<note place="margin">Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> each Chriſtian, may obſerve fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> henc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>God's Power, Wiſdome, and great Providence,</l>
                     <l>Who order'd all; to Holy ends herein,</l>
                     <l>Yet was no Author, of this grievous ſin.</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Adam's</hi> fall; all men have inclination,</l>
                     <l>To every ſin, and all their Generation.</l>
                     <l>And are bound over, to the wrath of God,</l>
                     <l>Curſe of the Law, and his deſtroying Rod.</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49076:26"/>
                     <l>Now ſee compaſſion, in this woful caſe,</l>
                     <l>God offers Man,<note place="margin">Of the Covenac of grace</note> a Covenant of Grace:</l>
                     <l>That all th'elect by Faith might ſaved be,</l>
                     <l>Both Jew and Gentile none excepted he.</l>
                     <l>Beleive and live God offers Chriſt to thee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f thou accept him, hel'e a Saviour be.</l>
                     <l>A Prophet, Prieſt and eke a Royal King,</l>
                     <l>Right Heire of all things, is this Holy thing.</l>
                     <l>Head of the Church, Redeemer of the ſame,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udge of the world, Chriſt Jeſus is his name.</l>
                     <l>Twixt God and man, he is the great Peace-maker,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urely for Saints, the only Mediator.</l>
                     <l>Equal with God, yet did aſſume the nature</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Adams</hi> ſeed (faln man) a ſinful creature.</l>
                     <l>Yet without ſin, but not infirmities,</l>
                     <l>He had a ſence of all man's miſeries.</l>
                     <l>Conceaved by the Holy Ghoſt he was,</l>
                     <l>And through the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> Womb did paſs,</l>
                     <l>And of her ſubſtance, alſo did pertake,</l>
                     <l>And yet his God-head, he did not forſake.</l>
                     <l>Without Converſion, or Confuſion there,</l>
                     <l>Godhead and Manhood, both conjoyned were.</l>
                     <l>And doth remain, without a ſeperation,</l>
                     <l>Both God and man, the God of our ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>Who was Anointed, with the holy ſpirit</l>
                     <l>That he might mediate, for man and merit.</l>
                     <l>He undefiled was, and full of grace,</l>
                     <l>And fitted for, a Mediators place.</l>
                     <l>And from his Father, he receiv'd command</l>
                     <l>Who put all power, and judgement in his hand:</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49076:27"/>
                     <l>To undertake, and execute the ſame,</l>
                     <l>For th' good of man, and glory of his name.</l>
                     <l>That God and man, might reconciled be,</l>
                     <l>And Chriſt do all things that might make him fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Chriſt did this Office, freely undertake,</l>
                     <l>And did diſcharge it, for his ſervants ſake.</l>
                     <l>Which none could do but he, he did fulfil,</l>
                     <l>The Law exactly, and his Fathers will.</l>
                     <l>His ſoul and body under ſufferings were,</l>
                     <l>His bleſſed body,<note place="margin">The Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt.</note> peirced with a Spear.</l>
                     <l>This bleſſed man, on'th Croſs was Crucifi'd,</l>
                     <l>And for our ſins, our bleſſed Saviour dy'd:</l>
                     <l>To ſave the Saints, and free their Souls from pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>He dy'd for them; that they might live again.</l>
                     <l>Who all were dead, by <hi>Adam's</hi> ſinful Fall,</l>
                     <l>But now revived by Chriſt's Funeral.</l>
                     <l>Who all were ſlaves, till Jeſus made them free,</l>
                     <l>Till Chriſt did dye, and climb the curſed Tree.</l>
                     <l>When death dominion got, the power it kept,</l>
                     <l>Till the third day,<note place="margin">Of Chriſts reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention.</note> our Bleſſed Saviour ſlept,</l>
                     <l>Without Corruption, then he roſe again,</l>
                     <l>And conquer'd death and Hell, and deadly pain</l>
                     <l>And the ſame body, which in earth did lie,</l>
                     <l>Aſſended up, into the Heavens high.</l>
                     <l>And is exalted to the Throne of Grace,</l>
                     <l>By God his Father in a glorious place.</l>
                     <l>There to remain, until he ſhall deſcend,</l>
                     <l>To judge the world, when it ſhall have an end:</l>
                     <l>Our Saviour was, a Holy Sacrifice,</l>
                     <l>One offer'd up to God, which ſatisfi'd</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:49076:27"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s Fathers juſtice, and hath reconcil'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>im to th'elect, by <hi>Adam's</hi> fall defil'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he womans ſeed did break the Serpents head,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Lamb was ſlain for Saints and buried.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt hath Redemption, purchaſed, for men,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd interceſſion he doth make for them.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hoſe he redeem'd, to them he doth apply,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his purchaſe made (by him) effectually.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd by his word a perfect Declaration,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eveal'd to them, of th' miſteries of ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd by his ſpirit, in their inner parts,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oth work Obedience, and doth guide their hearts.</l>
                     <l>And all their enemies, he doth overcome,</l>
                     <l>By's Power, Wiſdome, and Dominion.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Free Will.</head>
                     <l>MAn in the ſtate of Innocency had,</l>
                     <l>A power to will, and do both good and bad.</l>
                     <l>He badly did, and he by doing ill,</l>
                     <l>Loſt both the power and freedome of his will.</l>
                     <l>He diſobey'd, and loſt his happy ſtation,</l>
                     <l>To will or do, what might obtain Salvation.</l>
                     <l>To what is good, he wholly is averſe,</l>
                     <l>And alſo dead, in ſins and treſpaſſes.</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49076:28"/>
                     <l>Man of himſelf, thus merg'd in miſery,</l>
                     <l>Can nothing do, for his recovery:</l>
                     <l>Till God convert him; and do him tranſlate,</l>
                     <l>Into a godly and a gracious ſtate.</l>
                     <l>Then he doth free him, from his natural ſin,</l>
                     <l>And from the bondage, he before was in.</l>
                     <l>And by his Grace, doth give him power and skill,</l>
                     <l>Spiritual works, as well to do, as will.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtill the ſeeds, of unregeneration,</l>
                     <l>Remain in him, till death remove his ſtation.</l>
                     <l>And when he comes, into eternal bliſs.</l>
                     <l>Free to all good (and not till then) he is.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Efectual Calling.</head>
                     <l>ALL thoſe that unto life by God's decree,</l>
                     <l>Predeſtinated are aſſuredly:</l>
                     <l>His Heirs ſhall be, and Heaven ſhall inherit,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall be called, by his word and ſpirit.</l>
                     <l>Out of the ſtate of death, and deadly ſin,</l>
                     <l>In which by Nature, they were plunged in:</l>
                     <l>Into a ſtate of grace, and of Salvation,</l>
                     <l>By Jeſus Chriſt, and through his mediation.</l>
                     <l>And their blind minds, ſhall filled be with light,</l>
                     <l>To underſtand, the things of God aright,</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49076:28"/>
                     <l>From them ſhall taken be, their hearts of ſtone,</l>
                     <l>And hearts of fleſh, infuſed in the room,</l>
                     <l>And in their wills, they ſhall renewed be,</l>
                     <l>To do what's good; then grace ſhall make them free</l>
                     <l>This calling is by ſpecial grace alone</l>
                     <l>And not for any thing foreſeen or known,</l>
                     <l>That is in man: therein he paſſive is;</l>
                     <l>God by his ſpirit, freely calleth (his)</l>
                     <l>And them enables, alſo to embrace</l>
                     <l>His gracious offer, when he offers grace.</l>
                     <l>Elected Infants in their Infancy,</l>
                     <l>Are ſav'd by Chriſt, although the Infants die.</l>
                     <l>Perſons elect, depriv'd of outward call</l>
                     <l>By'th Miniſtry, yet they are ſaved all.</l>
                     <l>Men not elected, though they called be</l>
                     <l>By'th outward call, of word and Miniſtry.</l>
                     <l>And have ſome operation of the ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>ſhall not be ſaved, by Chriſt Jeſus merrit.</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that be not Chriſtians they can never,</l>
                     <l>Salvation have, by any way whatſoever.</l>
                     <l>Though they their lives, do frame by natures light,</l>
                     <l>And keep that Law, wherein they do delight.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49076:29"/>
                     <head>Of Iuſtification.</head>
                     <l>ALL thoſe that called are effectually,</l>
                     <l>The ſame God doth moſt freely juſtifie.</l>
                     <l>And into them, doth righteouſneſs infuſe,</l>
                     <l>They are the Children, God doth freely chuſe,</l>
                     <l>Their ſins he pardons, and their perſons takes,</l>
                     <l>As righteous all, for Chriſt our Saviour's ſake.</l>
                     <l>Not for the works or deeds, which they have done,</l>
                     <l>Their debts diſcharg'd, by Jeſus Chriſt (his Son)</l>
                     <l>He by his ſufferings. did acquit from ſin,</l>
                     <l>All thoſe that reſt, and do rely on him.</l>
                     <l>By lively faith, his righteouſneſs is theirs,</l>
                     <l>This Faith God gives to his Adopted Heirs.</l>
                     <l>And they receave the ſame beleivingly,</l>
                     <l>And by their faith, God doth them juſtifie.</l>
                     <l>All ſaying graces do attend this one,</l>
                     <l>Faith works by love, and never goes alone,</l>
                     <l>And for all thoſe that are thus juſtifi'd,</l>
                     <l>To anſwer Juſtice, our dear Saviour di'd,</l>
                     <l>Man's juſtify'd, this done, by Gods free grace,</l>
                     <l>And yet obſerve, that Juſtice keeps his place.</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49076:29"/>
                     <l>That all the elect, for which our Saviour dy'd,</l>
                     <l>By Gods decree, were freely juſtifi'd.</l>
                     <l>Yet though elected, they are not juſt men,</l>
                     <l>Till Chriſt by'th ſpirit, be apply'd to them.</l>
                     <l>Man juſtifi'd, can never loſe that treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Yet he by's ſins, may ſuffer Gods diſpleaſure.</l>
                     <l>And loſe the favour of his countenance,</l>
                     <l>Till he be humbled by true penitence.</l>
                     <l>And do confeſs his ſin, and pardon get,</l>
                     <l>Renew his faith, and ſo remove the lett.</l>
                     <l>Believers under, the Old Teſtament,</l>
                     <l>(As under new,) herein is alſo meant.</l>
                     <l>And of God's mercy, freely did pertake,</l>
                     <l>And juſtify'd were for our Saviours ſake.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Adoption.</head>
                     <l>ALL thoſe (by God) that juſtified be,</l>
                     <l>For his Sons ſake, adopted are and free.</l>
                     <l>God for his Children, them doth freely take,</l>
                     <l>They have acceſs unto the Throne of Grace,</l>
                     <l>And Abba Father, they may boldly cry,</l>
                     <l>And he will help them in their miſery.</l>
                     <l>He pities them, and them he doth protect,</l>
                     <l>He is their father and will them correct.</l>
                     <l>Yet he his Children never will forſake,</l>
                     <l>Co-heirs with Chriſt, he doth his Children make.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:49076:30"/>
                     <head>Of Sanctification.</head>
                     <l>ALL the Elect, that are regenerated,</l>
                     <l>In them new hearts and Spirits are created:</l>
                     <l>And all ſuch Saints are ſanctifyed more</l>
                     <l>By God's good ſpirit, then they were before.</l>
                     <l>And they not only are more ſanctifi'd</l>
                     <l>But ſins dominion, is in them deſtroy'd.</l>
                     <l>And that dominion being ſo deſtroy'd,</l>
                     <l>Their ſeveral Luſts, in them are mortifi'd.</l>
                     <l>More quickning and more fading graces then,</l>
                     <l>Appear in all ſuch ſanctified men:</l>
                     <l>More power they have to practiſe holineſs</l>
                     <l>Which brings them to eternal hapineſs,</l>
                     <l>Yet notwithſtanding; Saints proceed ſo far,</l>
                     <l>Still their corruptions, raiſe a dealy warr.</l>
                     <l>The fleſh and ſpirit, alwaies are at ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>Fleſh fights for death, the ſpirit ſtrives for life.</l>
                     <l>And in this fight, the fleſh doth many maime,</l>
                     <l>And then the ſpirit, conquer's it again.</l>
                     <l>And then the Saints, in ſaving graces grow,</l>
                     <l>More fleſh doth fight, more grace it ſelf doth ſhow.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49076:30"/>
                     <head>Of ſaving Faith.</head>
                     <l>By'th word and ſpirit, ſaving faith is wrought,</l>
                     <l>In all th'elect, and they thereby are brought;</l>
                     <l>Into the way that leads to perfect bliſs,</l>
                     <l>And then their Faith, by Prayer increaſed is.</l>
                     <l>Then by the Sacraments, they get more ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>By Faith in Chriſt, their ſouls are ſav'd at length.</l>
                     <l>By this true Faith; all Chriſtians do accord,</l>
                     <l>To all the truths, in the revealed word.</l>
                     <l>And ſquare their actions, by the Rule and Line,</l>
                     <l>Of God's good word, as he doth them incline.</l>
                     <l>Doing and ſuffering, what he doth require,</l>
                     <l>Doing the ſame, with hearts that are intire.</l>
                     <l>Trembling at threats, the promiſes imbraceing</l>
                     <l>Reſting on Chriſt our Saviour, for ſalvation.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Repentance unto Life.</head>
                     <l>BY Gods good ſpirit, and by his Holy Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which are as ſharp, as any edged ſword<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49076:31"/>
                     <l>True penitence, may be ſo wrought in him,</l>
                     <l>That was defiled, by notorious ſin,</l>
                     <l>That by Gods grace, and by the ſence and ſight,</l>
                     <l>Of ſins defilement, he may grow contrite</l>
                     <l>And greatly greive, that he did ever ſin,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the Lord, that ſuffer'd death for him:</l>
                     <l>And may endeavour, with a true intent,</l>
                     <l>To walk the waies of God's Commandements.</l>
                     <l>Man by Repentance, cannot pardon merit</l>
                     <l>And yet without it, cannot bliſs inherit.</l>
                     <l>No ſins ſo ſmall, but it deſerves damnation,</l>
                     <l>No ſin's ſo great, but man may have ſalvation;</l>
                     <l>By true Repentance, but obſerve herein,</l>
                     <l>He ought t'repent, of all and every ſin</l>
                     <l>And them confeſs to God, and them forſake,</l>
                     <l>And pray for pardon, for our Saviours ſake</l>
                     <l>And if he doth, his brother ſcandalize</l>
                     <l>Or the true Church in any wiſe,</l>
                     <l>He muſt confes't, and ſorrow for the ſame</l>
                     <l>And reconcile himſelf, to them again.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of good Works.</head>
                     <l>SUch works as God by's holy word commands,</l>
                     <l>Such he accepts, from all his peoples hands.</l>
                     <l>But ſuch as be the products of blind zeal,</l>
                     <l>Or mans device, ſhall not a whit avail.</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49076:31"/>
                     <l>Good works by men, done in obedience,</l>
                     <l>To Gods commands, are fruits and evidence.</l>
                     <l>Of true and lively Faith, and manifeſt,</l>
                     <l>That they by Faith do in aſſurance reſt:</l>
                     <l>And have a good and ſtrong, and full perſwaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Founded upon the promiſe, of ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>Men by good works their brethren edifie</l>
                     <l>Adorn Profeſſion and (God) glorifie.</l>
                     <l>They by their works, ſhew what they do profeſs,</l>
                     <l>Their faith produceth fruits of holineſs,</l>
                     <l>No man (good works) by his own power can do</l>
                     <l>The ſpirit doth inable him thereto.</l>
                     <l>Yet muſt he not, be negligent and ſin,</l>
                     <l>But muſt ſtir up the grace of God in him.</l>
                     <l>They that attain unto the greateſt height,</l>
                     <l>Yet their obedience alwaies wanteth weight</l>
                     <l>Man's ſhort of duty, in a ſinful ſtate,</l>
                     <l>How then can any ſuperorrogate?</l>
                     <l>No mortal man (for ſin) can pardon merit,</l>
                     <l>Such Popiſh thoughts, proceed from no good ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>When he hath done what ever he can do,</l>
                     <l>His duty he, cannot attain unto.</l>
                     <l>What good, man doth, proceedeth from the ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>What's wrought by him, is ſtaind, where's then the merit?</l>
                     <l>Yet as the perſons, of beleivers be,</l>
                     <l>By God (through Chriſt) accepted, ſo doth he,</l>
                     <l>Their works accept, yet ſtill its all through him,</l>
                     <l>For their beſt works defiled are with ſin.</l>
                     <l>But God accepts them, if they be ſincere,</l>
                     <l>And them rewards, as if they perfect were,</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49076:32"/>
                     <l>God doth not unbeleivers, workes accept,</l>
                     <l>And yet they ſin, if they good works neglect:</l>
                     <l>Their works proceed, from hearts not purifi'd</l>
                     <l>Therefore by them, God is not glorifi'd.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the perſeverance of the Saints</head>
                     <l>VVHom God accepted hath, for his ſons me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</l>
                     <l>And call'd and ſanctifi'd by his good ſpirit</l>
                     <l>They never can, (that are in ſuch a caſe)</l>
                     <l>Fall finally; from that good ſtate of Grace,</l>
                     <l>But ſhall therein continue to the end,</l>
                     <l>And then their ſouls, to Heaven ſhall aſcend</l>
                     <l>This perſeverance, wholly doth depend</l>
                     <l>On God's decree, which never hath an end:</l>
                     <l>And not upon th' free will of ſinful men,</l>
                     <l>But th' ſpirit's power, that inables them.</l>
                     <l>This floweth from, the love of God ſo free</l>
                     <l>In Chriſt, that it, can never changed be.</l>
                     <l>Yet through corruption, man may ſin commit,</l>
                     <l>And for a time, may take delight in it.</l>
                     <l>And may thereby, incurr the Lords diſpleaſure,</l>
                     <l>And be depriv'd of comfort in ſome meaſure,</l>
                     <l>And conſcience wound, and hardneſs have of heart</l>
                     <l>And eke of judgements, feel the weight and ſmart.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49076:32"/>
                     <head>Of the Aſſurance of Grace and Salvation.</head>
                     <l>THough Hypocrites, and unregenerate,</l>
                     <l>May through falſe hopes, miſtake their own eſtate:</l>
                     <l>And thereupon preſume of their ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>When they are in, the ſtate of deep damnation:</l>
                     <l>Yet true beleevers, may aſſured be,</l>
                     <l>Of their ſalvation, and felicity.</l>
                     <l>If for ſalvation, they on Chriſt rely,</l>
                     <l>By Faith; and love him in ſincerity.</l>
                     <l>Indeavouring good, deteſting every ſin,</l>
                     <l>A happy ſtate, are ſuch beleivers in.</l>
                     <l>And of ſalvation, may themſelves aſſure,</l>
                     <l>And happineſs that ſhall for aye endure.</l>
                     <l>Men may have Faith, and yet may not attain,</l>
                     <l>To full aſſurance, nor perceive the ſame.</l>
                     <l>For many times, God makes his Children waite,</l>
                     <l>And ſuffer conflicts, ere they do pertake</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch aſſurance; yet the Lord takes care</l>
                     <l>For their ſupport: and keeps them from deſpair.</l>
                     <l>And they that get aſſurance, of ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>Are not ſo ſure, but that it may be ſhaken.</l>
                     <l>For God the ſame, doth often intermit</l>
                     <l>When they are careleſs of preferring it.</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49076:33"/>
                     <l>Or do commit, ſome great and griveous ſin,</l>
                     <l>When by temptation Satan drawes them in,</l>
                     <l>Or if the Lord withdraw himſelf from them</l>
                     <l>They walk in darkneſs, like deſpairing men.</l>
                     <l>Yet when the Lord, thus for a time departs</l>
                     <l>He leaves his ſpirit, working in their hearts.</l>
                     <l>And he himſelf returns in his due time,</l>
                     <l>Then their aſſurance is reviv'd again,</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Religious Worſhip, and Reſt on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Lords Day.</head>
                     <l>THe light of nature, ſhewes, there is a Lord,</l>
                     <l>That rules and raigneth over all the world.</l>
                     <l>Good of himſelf, and doth do good to all,</l>
                     <l>Unto this God, we ought to cry and call:</l>
                     <l>Fear him and love him, truſt him day and night,</l>
                     <l>Praiſe him and ſerve him, with our hearts and mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtiō. </seg>
                        </label> But what's the Worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that will pleaſe the Lord</l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                        </label> Such as he hath revealed in his word.</l>
                     <l>Not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns device, not mans imagination,</l>
                     <l>Nor the ſuggeſtions, that proceed from Satan.</l>
                     <l>But Gods good word, preſcribes the ready way,</l>
                     <l>Walk in the ſame, Reſt on the Sabbath day.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49076:33"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49076:34"/>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:49076:34"/>
                     <l>Religious worſhip's, due to God alone,</l>
                     <l>To Angels, Saints, and other creatures none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>To Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, then pay,</l>
                     <l>This Holy Tribute, and no other way.</l>
                     <l>And that thy ſervice, may have acceptation,</l>
                     <l>Do all thou doſt, through Chriſt his mediation.</l>
                     <l>Prayer with thankſgiving, from a holy heart</l>
                     <l>Of this pure worſhip, is a ſpecial part:</l>
                     <l>By God required, from all ſorts of men,</l>
                     <l>But that it may accepted be from them:</l>
                     <l>It muſt be made, through Jeſus Chriſt the Son,</l>
                     <l>And by the help, of his good ſpirit done.</l>
                     <l>According to his will moſt reverently,</l>
                     <l>In faith and love with all humility.</l>
                     <l>And all ſuch Worſhip, (vocal) muſt be done</l>
                     <l>Not in the Popiſh way, but in the vulgar tongue.</l>
                     <l>We ought to pray, for all the ſorts of men,</l>
                     <l>But for the dead, we muſt not pray for them.</l>
                     <l>Nor pray for him, that doth of malice ſin,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the ſpirit, that enlightned him.</l>
                     <l>Read Holy Scriptures, with a godly fear,</l>
                     <l>Sound Preaching of the Word, eke gladly hear:</l>
                     <l>Perform theſe duties in Obedience,</l>
                     <l>Unto the Lord, with faith and reverence.</l>
                     <l>Singing of Pſalmes, with good and gracious hearts,</l>
                     <l>Receave the Sacraments, for they are parts.</l>
                     <l>Of that Religious Worſhip, God commands,</l>
                     <l>And doth expect, at all his peoples hands.</l>
                     <l>Beſides Religions Oathes, Vowes, ſolemn Faſts,</l>
                     <l>And eke Thankſgivings, for deliverance paſt,</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:49076:35"/>
                     <l>Religious Worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will accepted be,</l>
                     <l>In any place, performed reverently,</l>
                     <l>And is not ty'd, to places here or there,</l>
                     <l>God may be truly worſhipt every where.</l>
                     <l>In publick, private, or in families,</l>
                     <l>But yet more ſolemnly, in Church Aſſemblies:</l>
                     <l>Which wilfully, muſt not neglected be,</l>
                     <l>When God calls us, to ſuch ſolemnity.</l>
                     <l>One day in ſeven, wholly muſt be kept,</l>
                     <l>And for a Sabbath, muſt a part be ſet:</l>
                     <l>And ſolemniz'd, unto the living Lord,</l>
                     <l>According to his will and holy word.</l>
                     <l>The ſeventh day, the J with Sabbath was,</l>
                     <l>Till Jeſus Chriſt, from death to life did paſs.</l>
                     <l>Since on the firſt, it hath been kept alway,</l>
                     <l>And ſo is (now) the Chriſtian Sabbath day.</l>
                     <l>This Sabbath, to the Lord is holy kept,</l>
                     <l>When as the people do, with due reſpect.</l>
                     <l>To his commands, fit and prepare their hearts,</l>
                     <l>And worldly buſineſs, wholly ſet a part.</l>
                     <l>And do obſerve a holy reſt that day,</l>
                     <l>Not to their Recreations giving way:</l>
                     <l>Nor their own works, nor words, nor thoughts,</l>
                     <l>Works of neceſſity, and mercy yet we ought</l>
                     <l>To do: but we muſt alwaies careful be,</l>
                     <l>In all we do, to act Religiouſly.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49076:35"/>
                     <head>Of the Church.</head>
                     <l>ALL God's Elect that Heaven ſhall inherit,</l>
                     <l>And be by Faith, pertakers of Chriſt's merit</l>
                     <l>All thoſe the unive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal Church we call,</l>
                     <l>They are Chriſt's flock, and he the head of all,</l>
                     <l>Out of all Nations, is this flock ſelected,</l>
                     <l>Clens'd by Chriſts Blood, and by himſelf accepted</l>
                     <l>And the whole number of th'elected ones,</l>
                     <l>That have been, are, or ſhall be he will own.</l>
                     <l>The Church of Chriſt, which viſible we call,</l>
                     <l>And under the Goſpel, is Catholicall</l>
                     <l>Conſiſts of them and theirs, that do profeſs,</l>
                     <l>The true Religion, and true Holineſs.</l>
                     <l>Out of this way, can no ſure expectation</l>
                     <l>Be had by any, of their ſouls ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>Unto the Church, Chriſt gave the Miniſtry</l>
                     <l>Which by his ſpirit, works effectually.</l>
                     <l>For gathering, and for making perfect (his)</l>
                     <l>That are elected, to eternal bliſs</l>
                     <l>And of this Church, Chriſt Jeſus is the head,</l>
                     <l>And by his ſpirit, are his people lead.</l>
                     <l>The Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> cannot in any ſence</l>
                     <l>Be Head thereof, you may collect from hence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>That he's the Anti-Chriſt, and man of ſin,</l>
                     <l>That doth oppoſe Chriſts holy Church, and him.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:49076:36"/>
                     <head>Of the Communion of Saints.</head>
                     <l>ALL Saints to Jeſus Chriſt their head; are knit</l>
                     <l>By's ſpirit and faith, and have a fellowſhip</l>
                     <l>With him in's ſufferings, death, and in his graces</l>
                     <l>His Reſurrection; and in (happy caſes)</l>
                     <l>Are all ſuch Saints, and Heaven ſhall inherit,</l>
                     <l>And eke pettake of Chriſt and all his merits.</l>
                     <l>So all ſuch Saints, to one another knit</l>
                     <l>In love, begets a holy fellowſhip.</l>
                     <l>They have Communion, in each others graces</l>
                     <l>Share in their Prayers, and in their hearts have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</l>
                     <l>And are oblig'd, ſuch duties to perform,</l>
                     <l>Publick and private, as may them concern.</l>
                     <l>And to their mutual good, conducing be,</l>
                     <l>Both to the outward man, and inwardly.</l>
                     <l>This fellowſhip, which Saints, with Chriſt injoy,</l>
                     <l>In no reſpect, gives them equality,</l>
                     <l>With him, none of his Saints, or ſervants can,</l>
                     <l>Compare, as he, is either God or man.</l>
                     <l>Nor Saints Communion, never can deſtroy</l>
                     <l>In Goods or Lands, their ſole propriety.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49076:36"/>
                     <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
                     <l>BAptiſme is a Holy Sacrament,</l>
                     <l>Which doth to us, moſt lively repreſent,</l>
                     <l>The powerful waſhing of the blood and ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Of Chriſt; that did for all beleivers merit.</l>
                     <l>Into the Church, they have initiation,</l>
                     <l>And ſignes and ſeales, of their regeneration,</l>
                     <l>Pardon of ſins, is eke confirm'd to them,</l>
                     <l>And into Chriſt, they are ingrafted then.</l>
                     <l>They ſin that do, this Ordinance neglect,</l>
                     <l>Salvation yet, to it's, not ſo anext</l>
                     <l>But that without it infants may be ſaved,</l>
                     <l>And ſome into Perdition go, that have it.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Lords Supper.</head>
                     <l>THis ordinance unto the ſoul is ſweet,</l>
                     <l>Where there is faith, and where the Heart's upright,</l>
                     <l>What empty, poor, and barren things are then,</l>
                     <l>The Sacraments, to unbeleiving men?</l>
                     <l>Get faith, Repent, draw neer to God and pray,</l>
                     <l>Uſe ordinances in a Holy way.</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49076:37"/>
                     <l>Tis great diſhonour, to the God of might,</l>
                     <l>When men, his holy Ordinances ſleight,</l>
                     <l>O then call in for all the ſtock of grace,</l>
                     <l>Stir up affections, in this weighty caſe.</l>
                     <l>Firſt get your ſins, ſlain by the edged ſword,</l>
                     <l>Of Gods good ſpirit in the Holy Word</l>
                     <l>Excite your faith, Repentance exerciſe,</l>
                     <l>Forſake all ſins, and buy the Pearl of priſe,</l>
                     <l>Faith is the Captain and the Maſter-grace,</l>
                     <l>Faith his our ſouls, our Saviour to embrace.</l>
                     <l>Faith is a Jewel, faith doth juſtifie,</l>
                     <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> faith on Chriſt, poor ſinners do rely.</l>
                     <l>Faith gives us intereſt, in his benefits,</l>
                     <l>Faith, weary ſouls, for Grace and mercy fits.</l>
                     <l>Faith, gives us intereſt, in Chriſt's blood and merit,</l>
                     <l>Faith, makes Chriſt ours, both in his grace &amp; ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Faith makes the ſoul, his Saviour apprehend,</l>
                     <l>The grace of faith, our ſouls to Chriſt commend.</l>
                     <l>By faith, we do, our Saviours body eate.</l>
                     <l>By faith, Chriſts body, we receave for meat:</l>
                     <l>By faith, we drink our bleſſed Saviours blood,</l>
                     <l>Our Saviours Body, is his ſervants food</l>
                     <l>The matter of the Sacrament indeed,</l>
                     <l>Is Chriſt himſelf, whereon we chiefly feed.</l>
                     <l>By him, we nouriſh'd are, our ſins are kil'd,</l>
                     <l>By Chriſts warm blood, our ſouls with Grace are fil'd</l>
                     <l>O ſin-ſick ſoul, canſt thou more dainties wiſh</l>
                     <l>Then to be nouriſh'd, by this Princely Diſh?</l>
                     <l>Hath Chriſt provided, ſinners ſuch a Feaſt?</l>
                     <l>By which their graces are ſo much increaſt</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49076:37"/>
                     <l>O then praiſe God, flie evill, follow good,</l>
                     <l>Thy filthy ſins, have ſhed thy Saviours blood.</l>
                     <l>All wicked perſons and impenitent,</l>
                     <l>Pertake not of, this bleſſed Sacrament.</l>
                     <l>For graceleſs perſons, by the ſame grow worſe,</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of bleſſings, they obtain a curſe.</l>
                     <l>Grace in the Sacrament is never bred,</l>
                     <l>But grace by it's Increas'd and nouriſhed</l>
                     <l>They that come graceleſs thither, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aceleſs may<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Return from thence, and go much worſe away,</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The State of Man after Death, and of the Reſurrection of the Dead.</head>
                     <l>WHen men are dead, their mortal bodies muſt,</l>
                     <l>Both ſee corruption, and return to duſt.</l>
                     <l>And then their ſouls, which ſhall immortal be,</l>
                     <l>Return unto the Lord immediately.</l>
                     <l>The ſouls of Saints, that lived righteouſly</l>
                     <l>Are then receav'd into the Heavens high,</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49076:38"/>
                     <l>Where they behold Gods face, in glorious light,</l>
                     <l>Ath' day of Judgement ſouls and bodies meet.</l>
                     <l>The ſouls of wicked men, are ſent to Hell,</l>
                     <l>Where they in pain, and utter darkneſs dwell.</l>
                     <l>And are reſerv'd unto the judgement day,</l>
                     <l>Then to receive their dreadful doom for aye.</l>
                     <l>Two places, only God, for ſouls created,</l>
                     <l>When ſouls and bodies ſhould be ſeperated,</l>
                     <l>At'h day of Judgement, ſuch as lite enjoy</l>
                     <l>Shall all be changed: but they ſhall not die.</l>
                     <l>And all the dead, that day ſhall raiſed be,</l>
                     <l>With the ſame bodies, not ſuch qualities</l>
                     <l>And to their ſouls, united be again,</l>
                     <l>Some doom'd to bliſs, ſome to eternal pain.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the laſt Judgement.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GOd hath appointed, Jeſus Chriſt his Son,</l>
                        <l>To judge the World; and to pronounce the doom</l>
                        <l>Of wicked Angels, and all earthly men,</l>
                        <l>Who ſhall appear, and ſhall be judged then,</l>
                        <l>By Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall in glory ſit,</l>
                        <l>Condemn the wicked, and the Godly quit.</l>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49076:38"/>
                        <l>This day of Judgement, it ſhall ſurely come,</l>
                        <l>God knowes the time, and none but he alone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O Watch, and Pray; then night and day,</l>
                        <l>God's Lawes obey, that Chriſt may ſay,</l>
                        <l>Thou haſt done faithfully:</l>
                        <l>Thou haſt well done: O therefore come,</l>
                        <l>And enter into Joy.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:39"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:39"/>
                  <p>POEMS Againſt POPERY: COMPOSED</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Edward Manlove</hi> of <hi>Aſhborn</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby</hi> Eſquier.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, for <hi>Richard Mills</hi> at the Peſtel and Mortar without <hi>Temple Barr.</hi> 1667.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:40"/>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49076:40"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <l>PEruſe theſe Poems, dreſt in mean attire,</l>
                  <l>Love truth, hate error heartily deſire,</l>
                  <l>To follow Peace, and worſhip God aright,</l>
                  <l>Obſerve the Scriptures, Romiſh errors ſleight.</l>
                  <l>The Roman Church, did Chriſt her Spouſe forſake,</l>
                  <l>And to her Idols, did her ſelf betake.</l>
                  <l>She is unclean, defil'd with ſpots and ſtaines,</l>
                  <l>Unſound, corrupt, but yet a Church remains.</l>
                  <l>Therefore beware, of utter deteſtation,</l>
                  <l>Of all her doctrine, all's not Innovation.</l>
                  <l>Truth's fundamental, which themſelves deſcrie,</l>
                  <l>By their bright luſtre do not thou deny,</l>
                  <l>But them imbrace, and ſhun what is unſound,</l>
                  <l>Coyne currant is, that's in a channel found,</l>
                  <l>Refuſe the Chaff, do not the Wheat reject,</l>
                  <l>Hate Hereſie but wholſome Truths reſpect.</l>
                  <l>They hold three perſons in the Trinity,</l>
                  <l>We hold the ſame, and do them deifie.</l>
                  <l>But for their error, and their falſe Tradition,</l>
                  <l>They do deſerve our utter oppoſition,</l>
                  <l>Regard them not, beleive not Romiſh Fables,</l>
                  <l>Abhor their Idols, Croſſes, Beades, and Bables.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> which Pope <hi>Urban</hi> tells</l>
                  <l>Will work ſtrauge feats, and evil ſprights diſpel,</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:49076:41"/>
                  <l>Their creeping crouch, their kiſſing of the Pax,</l>
                  <l>Their Medals, Roſes, and ſuch Romiſh knacks.</l>
                  <l>Their hallowed ſwords, their falſe equivocations,</l>
                  <l>In ſacred Oathes, their mental reſervations,</l>
                  <l>Their worſhiping of wooden ſtock and ſtones,</l>
                  <l>Their Adoration of old rotten bones.</l>
                  <l>Their Altars Veſtures, Images and Tapers,</l>
                  <l>Their Cenſings, Offerings, Shrifes, and holy Waters.</l>
                  <l>Their new found Faith, of Tranſubſtantiation,</l>
                  <l>Their Prayers to Saints a Popiſh Innovation,</l>
                  <l>Their Cancelling Chriſt's Will and Teſtament,</l>
                  <l>By mangling of the Holy Sacrament.</l>
                  <l>Their Bulls their Pardons and their Purgatory,</l>
                  <l>Their Latine ſervice and ſuch Ceremony,</l>
                  <l>Their Pilgrimage their Merits and Proceſſions,</l>
                  <l>Their five new Sacraments, their forc'd Confeſſions,</l>
                  <l>Their deifying of the Romiſh Whore,</l>
                  <l>Vain ſacrifice and many errors more.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Popiſh errors, totally diſcard,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Apiſh toyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (good Reader) diſregard,</l>
                  <l>And ſo farwel, what followes now peruſe</l>
                  <l>Imbrace the Truth, my errors all excuſe.</l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poems">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49076:41"/>
                  <head>POEMS Againſt Popery.</head>
                  <byline>Compoſed by <hi>Edward Manlove</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </byline>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>I.</hi> Againſt the Popiſh Tenent of Juſtification by inherent Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</head>
                     <l>INherent Juſtice no man Juſtifies,</l>
                     <l>Our Righteouſneſs, in Chriſt our Saviour lies,</l>
                     <l>And his, made ours, by faith it doth ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>To make us Righteous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Gods Righteous Eyes.</l>
                     <l>And all his Members clearly will acquit,</l>
                     <l>A'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h Judgement ſear, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall ſit,</l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49076:42"/>
                     <l>The Romiſh Whore, a Baſtard brood did nurſe,</l>
                     <l>Who blaſt this truth, with a tridentine curſe,</l>
                     <l>Chriſt's righteouſneſs, (imputed) muſt give pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>To righteouſneſs, by our inherent grace,</l>
                     <l>This horrid point, <hi>Pelagius,</hi> did invent,</l>
                     <l>And 'twas confirmed, at the Councel <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till then, this point of Faith, did not intrude,</l>
                     <l>Till then, this error, Councels did exclude.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Alſo</hi> Chriſoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nard, Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</note>Which now for truth the Romiſh Church reteit</l>
                     <l>This new ſound faith, doth ſtill at <hi>Rome</hi> remain,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth, this Popiſh point deny,</l>
                     <l>Inherent juſtice cannot juſtifie.</l>
                     <l>In vain the Papiſts wrangle and diſpute,</l>
                     <l>This Popiſh point, which Scripture doth confute</l>
                     <l>We are unjuſt, our hearts are all unclean,</l>
                     <l>Our righteouſneſs,<note place="margin">Ec. 7.20 Pr. 20.9 Eſ. 64.6. Ro. 7.23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> as filthy raggs remain.</l>
                     <l>And in our members, are the law o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſin,</l>
                     <l>Which leads us Captain, waging war therein,</l>
                     <l>In many things, all mortal men offend</l>
                     <l>We ſinners are,<note place="margin">James 3.2. Joh. 1.8. Act. 13.39. Rom 3.24. Eph 8.9 2 Cori. 5.21.</note> till ſinful life do end.</l>
                     <l>We are deceived if we do deny,</l>
                     <l>This ſacred truth, and full of falcity,</l>
                     <l>Through faith in Chriſt beleivers are made juſt,</l>
                     <l>By his free grace, to works we dare not truſt.</l>
                     <l>Our bleſſed Saviour, was for us made ſin,</l>
                     <l>And we the righteouſneſs of God, in him.</l>
                     <l>Can filthy raggs poor ſinners juſtifie?</l>
                     <l>Or ſave them from eternal miſery?</l>
                     <l>Repent, beleive, to God for mercy pray:</l>
                     <l>Chriſt's blood alone, can waſh thy ſins away.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49076:42"/>
                     <head>Againſt the Doctrine of Merit</head>
                     <l>HOw can man merit? all that he can do,</l>
                     <l>Is leſs then duty, ſtrictly ties him to.</l>
                     <l>And halfe done duties, how ſhould God reſpect?</l>
                     <l>Or what reward is due for ſuch neglect?</l>
                     <l>Eternal death, is wages due for ſin,</l>
                     <l>Neglect of duty needs muſt fall therein.</l>
                     <l>Through Jeſus Chriſt, God gives eternal bliſs,<note place="margin">Ro. 6.13</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Salvation comes, no other way but this.</l>
                     <l>God, works accepts, if faith do them evert,</l>
                     <l>And them rewards, but not for their deſert.</l>
                     <l>Theſe merit-mongers, therefore much miſtake</l>
                     <l>That look for Heaven, for their merits ſake.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</head>
                     <l>THe Romiſh Prelates, labour by coertion,</l>
                     <l>To make men own, this marvellous converſion</l>
                     <l>Have Prieſts ſuch power, by words of conſecration,</l>
                     <l>Of Bread and Wine, to make ſuch tranſmutation?</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:49076:43"/>
                     <l>A point Prodigious, that a Popiſh Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>Can make his God, or re-create his Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>This Novelty, of Tranſubſtantiation,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Lateran</hi> Councel,<note place="margin">An. dom 1215 500. years before.</note> had its confirmation.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> may Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> quote,</l>
                     <l>Who long before, againſt this error wrote.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Cockatrice,</hi> was hatcht in latter time,</l>
                     <l>Nurſt up at <hi>Rome,</hi> by ſuch as <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This Monſtrous Bratt, the Roman Church begot</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Greeks</hi> abhor'd it, Ancients own'd it not.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> he, doth learnedly maintain,</l>
                     <l>That Bread and Wine ſubſtantially remain.</l>
                     <l>The Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor 11.26.</note> that after conſecration,</l>
                     <l>The bread is bread, wher's then this tranſmutation</l>
                     <l>How can Chriſt's body, crucifi'd for thee,</l>
                     <l>At once,<note place="margin">Acts 3.21. Binius</note> in many thouſand places be?</l>
                     <l>If thou remain in Chriſt, and Chriſt in thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt receiv'd this ſacred Miſtery.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Doctrine of the Half Communion.</head>
                     <l>THis <hi>Romiſh</hi> error,<note place="margin">Anno 1453</note> lately ſtarted up,</l>
                     <l>The Councel <hi>Conſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> took away the Cup.</l>
                     <l>And thus they then, preſumptuouſly did wrent,</l>
                     <l>Our Saviours bleſſed will, and Teſtament.</l>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49076:43"/>
                     <l>By Chriſts Example, they will not be lead,</l>
                     <l>They to the <hi>Laicks,</hi> only give the bread.</l>
                     <l>Though Chriſt himſelf all Chriſtians do enjoyn</l>
                     <l>To eat the Bread, and alſo drink the Wine.</l>
                     <l>Yet Popiſh Prelates,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> Chriſt's Commandment ſleight</l>
                     <l>And rob his people of a holy right.</l>
                     <l>By this Preſumption, all may plainly ſee,</l>
                     <l>How Sacriledgious, Popiſh Prelates be.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt Miſſal Sacrifice.</head>
                     <l>OUr Bleſſed Saviour,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10.11.12.13.14.</note> on the Croſs,</l>
                     <l>A ſacrifice for ſin,</l>
                     <l>His body offered, once, for all,</l>
                     <l>For ſuch as truſt in him.</l>
                     <l>There needs no further ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>Our ſins to do away.</l>
                     <l>Vain is the Miſſal ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>That's offer'd every day.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt Image Worſhip.</head>
                     <l>THis Worſhip well deſerves the name,</l>
                     <l>Of groſs Idolatry,</l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:49076:44"/>
                     <l>God's holy word's, againſt the ſame,</l>
                     <l>And all Antiquity.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Lev. 26. ver. 1. Deut. 16.22. Eſa. 42 17, &amp; 45 16. Deut. 27 15. Mic. 5.13.</note>Ye ſhall your ſelves no Idol make,</l>
                     <l>Nor Graven Image reare,</l>
                     <l>Nor bow to it, nor Worſhip give,</l>
                     <l>The Scripture makes it clear.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt Papal Indulgences and Purgatory.</head>
                     <l>THe Romiſh Clergy, labour much,</l>
                     <l>This error to maintain,</l>
                     <l>This fire doth make their Kitchins ſmoak,</l>
                     <l>This craſt, brings in their gain.</l>
                     <l>This brings their Pardons into play,</l>
                     <l>This puts them off, with ſpeed.</l>
                     <l>To all ſuch ſilly ſouls as do,</l>
                     <l>Beleive the <hi>Romiſh Creed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This dreadful Doctrine, makes mens hearts</l>
                     <l>To tremble and to fear,</l>
                     <l>Away for Pardons then they pack,</l>
                     <l>Although they buy them dear.</l>
                     <l>Yet there's no torment after death,</l>
                     <l>To thoſe that faithful be,</l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49076:44"/>
                     <l>Their ſins diſperſed as a Cloud,</l>
                     <l>And their iniquity</l>
                     <l>They into judgement ſhall not come,</l>
                     <l>Their ſouls are free from pain.</l>
                     <l>And in eternal peace and joy,</l>
                     <l>For ever ſhall remain.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt Divine Worſhip, in an unknown Tongue.</head>
                     <l>BArbarian like, thoſe Bablers are,</l>
                     <l>That Service ſay, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cant</l>
                     <l>In Greek or Latine unto thoſe,</l>
                     <l>That underſtanding want.</l>
                     <l>This profits not, 'tis not the way,</l>
                     <l>God's Glory to advan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</l>
                     <l>This Romiſh practice in the Church,</l>
                     <l>Produceth Ignorance.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 5, 6, 9, 11, 13 14, 23.</note>Five words with underſtanding ſpoke,</l>
                     <l>More profits people then,</l>
                     <l>Ten thouſand words, in unknown tongues</l>
                     <l>Spoke to unlearned men.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49076:45"/>
                     <head>Againſt forced Sacramental Confeſſion.</head>
                     <l>BOth good, and beneficial uſe,</l>
                     <l>There may be of Confeſſion,</l>
                     <l>By ſuch as burden'd are with ſin,</l>
                     <l>And griev'd for great tranſgreſſion.</l>
                     <l>But ſetting them upon the rack,</l>
                     <l>And ſtraining them ſo high,</l>
                     <l>As ſtrict confeſſion of all ſins,</l>
                     <l>Is Romiſh Tyranny.</l>
                     <l>No ſuch Confeſſion, is requir'd,</l>
                     <l>As doth to ſin invite,</l>
                     <l>And nameing fleſhly pleaſures doth,</l>
                     <l>Much move the Appetite.</l>
                     <l>For who can tell how oft he ſins?</l>
                     <l>Or gives to God offence,</l>
                     <l>He alwaies ſins that ſo preſumes,</l>
                     <l>Upon his innocence.</l>
                     <l>As that he can enumerate,</l>
                     <l>His great tranſgreſſions all,</l>
                     <l>For he that thinks them leſs then great,</l>
                     <l>Doth into greater fall.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt did not to the ſinner ſay,</l>
                     <l>That had Faith and Contrition,</l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49076:45"/>
                     <l>Thy ſins muſt numbred be, or elſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt have no remiſſion,</l>
                     <l>He Abſolution freely gives,</l>
                     <l>Unto his children dear,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Mar. 9.2</note>Thy ſins forgiven are ſaith he,</l>
                     <l>My ſon be of good chear.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt Invocation of Saints.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">1 Kings 8.39. Eccl. 9.5.6 Eſai. 62.16. Pſ. 7.10.44.20. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.9.4.11. Prov. 15.10 &amp; 17.3. &amp; 24.12. Jer. 21, 20, &amp; 87 10, &amp; 10 11. Pſal. 50, 14, <hi>Againſt</hi> Eph, 2.8</note>THe Saints in Heaven do not know,</l>
                     <l>Our hearts they cannot hear,</l>
                     <l>Our Prayers, or ſupplications,</l>
                     <l>Made in this lower Sphear.</l>
                     <l>Our God alone, our Prayers doth hear,</l>
                     <l>Prayers made to Saints are vain,</l>
                     <l>God knowes the ſecrets of our ſouls,</l>
                     <l>And tryeth all our Reins.</l>
                     <l>Call on the name of God the Lord,</l>
                     <l>For eaſe in pain and grief,</l>
                     <l>And in thy greateſt troubles he,</l>
                     <l>Will ſend thy ſoul releif.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49076:46"/>
                     <head>Againſt the ſeven Sacraments.</head>
                     <l>OUr bleſſed Saviour, none but he,</l>
                     <l>Could make a Sacrament,</l>
                     <l>He made but two he made no more,</l>
                     <l>Is very evident.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10 1, 2, 3 4. St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
                        </note>Baptiſme, the Supper of the Lord,</l>
                     <l>Theſe flowed like a flood</l>
                     <l>Out of the ſide of Jeſus Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>In Water and in Blood.</l>
                     <l>The one it is the Sacrament,</l>
                     <l>Of our Initiation,</l>
                     <l>The other Sacrament is for,</l>
                     <l>Our holy confirmation.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Doctrine of Tradition.</head>
                     <l>THe Law of God's, a perfect law,</l>
                     <l>And needeth no ſupply,</l>
                     <l>What's needful to ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>Is fully taught thereby.</l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49076:46"/>
                     <l>In vain do many worſhip God,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Matth. 15.9.</note>And teach for doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine ſound,</l>
                     <l>Commandements o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ked men,</l>
                     <l>Thus errors do abound.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Univerſal Headſhip, of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>POpe <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, Inveighs,</l>
                     <l>Againſt this Lordly name,</l>
                     <l>As inſolent, the Churches plain</l>
                     <l>As wicked and Prophane.</l>
                     <l>A great corruption of the faith,</l>
                     <l>To God a great abuſe,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the Canons of the Church,</l>
                     <l>Againſt th'Apoſtles uſe.</l>
                     <l>Whoſoever uſe this lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty ſtile,</l>
                     <l>And glory in the ſame,</l>
                     <l>Forerunners are of Antichriſt,</l>
                     <l>And glory in their ſhame.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:49076:47"/>
                     <head>Againſt Challenged Infallibility.</head>
                     <l>THis Arrogation doth appear</l>
                     <l>A Paradox to be,</l>
                     <l>For former Popes, have fowlly faln,</l>
                     <l>Into flat Hereſie,</l>
                     <l>And Councels have condemned them,</l>
                     <l>For errors manifeſt,</l>
                     <l>The Councel held, at <hi>Baſil</hi> take,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Multi poncifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces erro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res &amp; he reſies lapſi eſſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur. <hi>Conſi. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil in Ep. Sinod.</hi>
                        </note>For one among the reſt.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Popes Superiority to General Councels.</head>
                     <l>VVEll near a thouſand Fathers of</l>
                     <l>The Romiſh Church did Vote,</l>
                     <l>Againſt this Dommineering Power,</l>
                     <l>Pretended by the Pope.</l>
                     <l>And in the Councel <hi>Conſtance</hi> thus,</l>
                     <l>Determin'd punctually.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">An. 1415</note>If General Councels make Decrees,</l>
                     <l>The Pope is bound thereby.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49076:47"/>
                     <head>Againſt the Preſumption of Papal Diſpenſations.</head>
                     <l>POpes had no power, in former time,</l>
                     <l>To grant a Diſpenſation,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gainſt Decrees, by Councels made,</l>
                     <l>This comes by Uſurpation.</l>
                     <l>Theſe boundleſs Diſpenſations, are,</l>
                     <l>A wicked Innovation,</l>
                     <l>This great Preſumption plainly ſhewes,</l>
                     <l>The Popes degeneration.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Againſt the Popes Domineering over Kings and Emperours.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Po. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory <hi>ſaid thus</hi> Mauriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vobis Obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidero.</note>THe Pope to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> came,</l>
                     <l>With Cap and bended knee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut now the greateſt Monarch muſt</l>
                     <l>Stoop to the Romiſh See.</l>
                     <l>Now Popes their lawful Soveraign ſleight,</l>
                     <l>Theſe Prelates greater be,</l>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:49076:48"/>
                     <l>Then all the Princes of the World,</l>
                     <l>In Power and Dignity.</l>
                     <l>Now Popes pretend a lawful power,</l>
                     <l>Their Emperours to dethrone</l>
                     <l>And of their Empires to diſpoſe,</l>
                     <l>As if they were their own.</l>
                     <l>The Emperour like a Serving man,</l>
                     <l>When as the Pope commands,</l>
                     <l>Muſt hold a Baſin, whilſt that he,</l>
                     <l>Doth waſh his Holy Hands.</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes like a Stable Groom</l>
                     <l>His Horſe, muſt lead and guide,</l>
                     <l>And hold his Stirrup, whilſt that he,</l>
                     <l>On Horsback, gets to ride.</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes like a Porter muſt,</l>
                     <l>Upon his Shoulder bear,</l>
                     <l>His Holineſs (the Pope forſooth)</l>
                     <l>And Homage to him ſwear.</l>
                     <l>This domineering over Kings,</l>
                     <l>And Emperours doth ſhew,</l>
                     <l>How Pontificial Prelates have,</l>
                     <l>Rob'd <hi>Caeſar</hi> of his due,</l>
                     <l>Theſe Romiſh Tricks, in former times,</l>
                     <l>Nor better were then Treaſon,</l>
                     <l>Againſt God's holy Word, they are,</l>
                     <l>Againſt both right and reaſon.</l>
                     <l>All Chriſtian Kings, and Princes great,</l>
                     <l>Abhorr the Romiſh Whore,</l>
                     <l>Break off her Bonds, caſt off her Yoak,</l>
                     <l>And never own h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r more.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49076:48"/>
                  <head>A form of Prayer Compoſed in Meeter,</head>
                  <byline>
                     <hi>By Edward Manlove <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                     </hi>
                  </byline>
                  <l>O God moſt great, whoſe Glorious ſeat.</l>
                  <l>Is in the Heavens high,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t thy command: both Sea and Land,</l>
                  <l>Obey thy Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd at thy will, the Seas ſtand ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And neither rage nor foame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom ſide to ſide, to Winds and Tide,</l>
                  <l>Thou mak'ſt thy power known.</l>
                  <l>Thou glorious art, in every part,</l>
                  <l>Thou art Omnipotent,</l>
                  <l>Be't far or near, thou dwelleſt there,</l>
                  <l>Thou art Omniſcient.</l>
                  <l>The Heavens high, nor lofty skie,</l>
                  <l>Thy Glory can contemn,</l>
                  <l>Thou raign'ſt on high, thy Majeſty</l>
                  <l>Doth Winds and Waves reſtraine.</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that do, by ſhipping go,</l>
                  <l>Into the Waters deep,</l>
                  <l>By works of wonder, and words like thunder,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhew'ſt thy power and might,</l>
                  <l>And thou the Storm, turn'ſt to a calme</l>
                  <l>And then the Waves are ſtill</l>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:49076:49"/>
                  <l>Thou makeſt glad, them that were ſad,</l>
                  <l>And ſav'ſt them from all ill,</l>
                  <l>We therefore all, may fear to call,</l>
                  <l>Upon thy dreadful name.</l>
                  <l>For our vile lips, they are unfit,</l>
                  <l>To nominate the ſame.</l>
                  <l>We here abide, the ſtubble dry'd,</l>
                  <l>Thou art conſuming fire,</l>
                  <l>Thou might's us burn, and make us turn,</l>
                  <l>To aſhes in thine ire.</l>
                  <l>In our own eyes, we all are vile,</l>
                  <l>Our waies are very wicked,</l>
                  <l>Then in thy ſight, whoſe eyes are bright,</l>
                  <l>How ſhall we be acquitted?</l>
                  <l>We are unfit, to kneel or fit</l>
                  <l>Before thy gracious Throne,</l>
                  <l>Or to draw nigh, thy Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>To make our caſes known.</l>
                  <l>But Lord we come, to thee alone,</l>
                  <l>For Jeſus Chriſt his ſake,</l>
                  <l>Accept our Prayers which we preſent</l>
                  <l>And through thy ſpirit make.</l>
                  <l>We are unworthy to be call'd</l>
                  <l>Thy ſons, or have the name,</l>
                  <l>Of any of thy ſervants; yea</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt of the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Our duties unto thee, and man,</l>
                  <l>(O Lord) we have neglected,</l>
                  <l>And not obey'd thy Holy Word,</l>
                  <l>But have thy Lawes rejected.</l>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49076:49"/>
                  <l>We have not honoured thee (O Lord)</l>
                  <l>With fear and reverence,</l>
                  <l>But ſin'd againſt thy juſt Precepts</l>
                  <l>By diſobedience.</l>
                  <l>O Lord we have not Worſhip'd thee,</l>
                  <l>According to thy will,</l>
                  <l>Nor in our hearts, have had delight,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſtatutes to fulfil,</l>
                  <l>But we confeſs, we have abus'd</l>
                  <l>Thy great and glorious name,</l>
                  <l>And alſo we, irreverently,</l>
                  <l>Have often us'd the ſame.</l>
                  <l>We have Prophan'd the Sabbath day,</l>
                  <l>In whole or elſe in part,</l>
                  <l>By needleſs thoughts, and words and works,</l>
                  <l>We all have carnal hearts.</l>
                  <l>By murderous thoughts, and wicked words,</l>
                  <l>We have our neighbours wrong'd</l>
                  <l>Our wicked words, have cut like ſwords,</l>
                  <l>We all have evil tongues.</l>
                  <l>We have not ſought, our neighbours good</l>
                  <l>Nor had a tender heart,</l>
                  <l>To our poor brethren in diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor pleaded on their part.</l>
                  <l>We have not viſited the ſick,</l>
                  <l>We have not cloath'd the naked,</l>
                  <l>We have not log'd the ſtranger, nor</l>
                  <l>Him compaſſionated.</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls and bodies are unclean,</l>
                  <l>By thoughts, and words, and actions.</l>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:49076:50"/>
                  <l>We have defil'd our ſinful ſouls</l>
                  <l>We have corrupt affections.</l>
                  <l>And rotten ſpeeches do proceed</l>
                  <l>From our corrupted hearts,</l>
                  <l>Our eyes and ears do let in ſins,</l>
                  <l>Which poyſon every part.</l>
                  <l>We have not made a Covenant,</l>
                  <l>With hearing ſight and ſenſes,</l>
                  <l>We have not watch'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and pray'd and faſted,</l>
                  <l>We have not ſhun'd intemperance.</l>
                  <l>We have not uſed all good means,</l>
                  <l>To further the eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Neither of our ſelves or neighbours, but</l>
                  <l>Have been inordinate,</l>
                  <l>We have not labour'd to maintain,</l>
                  <l>Or juſtly to defend,</l>
                  <l>Our neighbours credit or good name,</l>
                  <l>For any holy end.</l>
                  <l>We have not been contented with,</l>
                  <l>Our Callings and Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>But have unjuſtly coveted,</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves to elevate.</l>
                  <l>Now Lord ſince we have ſinned ſo,</l>
                  <l>And done ſo wickedly,</l>
                  <l>We juſtly merit, to inherit</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Dathan's</hi> family,</l>
                  <l>Eternal pain and miſery,</l>
                  <l>VVithin the pit of Hell,</l>
                  <l>And with the Divel, and the damn'd</l>
                  <l>We do deſerve to dwell.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:51"/>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49076:51"/>
                  <l>For if thou didſt, not Angels ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Which had ſuch glorious ſtations,</l>
                  <l>But hurl'ſt them down, from Heaven high,</l>
                  <l>And from their habitations.</l>
                  <l>Into the place, and pains of Hell,</l>
                  <l>In darkneſs there to lye,</l>
                  <l>Who ſinned once, and ſin'd but once,</l>
                  <l>Againſt thy Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>And our firſt Parents did'ſt expel,</l>
                  <l>From pleaſant Paradiſe.</l>
                  <l>Who broke one law, and them to that</l>
                  <l>The Divel did intice:</l>
                  <l>What vengeance then, may we expect,</l>
                  <l>For all our filthineſs?</l>
                  <l>Who dayly ſin, like water drink,</l>
                  <l>And dayly do tranſgreſs.</l>
                  <l>And have not broken only one,</l>
                  <l>But all thy Lawes moſt holy,</l>
                  <l>Thy Precepts, Statutes and Commands,</l>
                  <l>We have neglected wholly.</l>
                  <l>Sin upon ſin we heaped have,</l>
                  <l>And do deſerve the ſentence,</l>
                  <l>Due unto thoſe, that thee oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſin without Repentance.</l>
                  <l>We all are vile, and wretched men,</l>
                  <l>Thy Law our ſouls condemns,</l>
                  <l>Yet Lord thy Goſpel us aſſures,</l>
                  <l>Thy Grace thy Law tranſcends.</l>
                  <l>Thy goodneſs doth delight to raigne,</l>
                  <l>Where ſins do moſt abound,</l>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49076:52"/>
                  <l>Thy mercies maſter all thy works,</l>
                  <l>Thy mercy wears the Crown.</l>
                  <l>O therefore Hallowed be thy name,</l>
                  <l>Who of thy ſelf art holy,</l>
                  <l>Thy judgements juſt, do ſhew the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Thou art a God of Glory.</l>
                  <l>Thou art Jehovah, Lord of Hoſts,</l>
                  <l>Thy power is very great,</l>
                  <l>Thou Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>We humbly thee intreat,</l>
                  <l>Give us ſuch knowledge of thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And of the Trinity.</l>
                  <l>And of thy word and works, that we</l>
                  <l>Thy Name may glorifie.</l>
                  <l>Good Lord let us, thy word beleive,</l>
                  <l>And fear thy dreadful name,</l>
                  <l>Good Lord grant us fidelity,</l>
                  <l>To Sanctifie the ſame.</l>
                  <l>O Lord make us, fear thee alone,</l>
                  <l>Give us Humility,</l>
                  <l>And Patience, that we from hence,</l>
                  <l>May yield moſt willingly.</l>
                  <l>And may ſubmit our ſelves unto,</l>
                  <l>Thy juſt correcting rod,</l>
                  <l>Who doſt in love, correct th'elect,</l>
                  <l>And art a gracious God.</l>
                  <l>O give us Grace, that we may praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And hallow thy great name,</l>
                  <l>And by our Converſations may,</l>
                  <l>Give Glory to the ſame.</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:49076:52"/>
                  <l>Lord let not ſin, nor Satan reigne,</l>
                  <l>But let thy Kingdome come,</l>
                  <l>And let thy ſpirit, in our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Strive for Dominion.</l>
                  <l>Aboliſh Satans Kingdome Lord,</l>
                  <l>And from captivity,</l>
                  <l>Inlarge thy Saints, and break their bands,</l>
                  <l>And ſet thy ſervants free,</l>
                  <l>Collect and gather thine Elect,</l>
                  <l>O, do it ſpeedily,</l>
                  <l>And to that end do thou ſet up,</l>
                  <l>A faithful Miniſtry.</l>
                  <l>And let the bleſſing of thy ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>Accompany thy word,</l>
                  <l>O ſlay the ſins of all thy Saints,</l>
                  <l>By that two edged Sword.</l>
                  <l>And dayly more, increaſe the gifts,</l>
                  <l>And graces of thy ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>In all thy Saints and ſervants that,</l>
                  <l>Thy Kingdome ſhall inherit.</l>
                  <l>And by thy word and ſpirit rule,</l>
                  <l>The hearts and lives of them,</l>
                  <l>Kill their corruptions, curb their luſts,</l>
                  <l>And make them watchful men.</l>
                  <l>Raiſe up Religious Magiſtrates,</l>
                  <l>That truly may adore,</l>
                  <l>The Beauty of the Spouſe of Chriſt</l>
                  <l>And hate the Romiſh Whore.</l>
                  <l>Root out dumb dogs, and purge the Church,</l>
                  <l>From all impurity,</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:49076:53"/>
                  <l>Remove thoſe Rocks that give offence,</l>
                  <l>Root out Idolatry,</l>
                  <l>Root out all greedy Wolves, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>Root out thoſe Currs with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>That fleece and fley, and ſnarle and bite,</l>
                  <l>And take no care to feed.</l>
                  <l>O finiſh (Lord) with haſt and ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>The Kingdome of thy Grace,</l>
                  <l>Call all th'lect, that are uncall'd</l>
                  <l>Give thine a glorious place.</l>
                  <l>Come quickly Lord, diſſolve the world,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy this earthly ſtation,</l>
                  <l>Shew thy reſpect, to thine elect,</l>
                  <l>O haſten their ſalvation.</l>
                  <l>Stir up thy ſtrength, and come at length,</l>
                  <l>Thy deadly foes deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Who do oppoſe, both thee and thoſe,</l>
                  <l>That love thy Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>On thee we reſt, thy time is beſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy bleſſed will be done,</l>
                  <l>O grant we may, from day to day,</l>
                  <l>Obey thee every one.</l>
                  <l>And that we may, thee ſo obey,</l>
                  <l>Lord grant that we from hence,</l>
                  <l>May willingly, ſubmit to thy</l>
                  <l>Good will and providence.</l>
                  <l>And all at once, may now renounce,</l>
                  <l>Our evil inclinations,</l>
                  <l>The World, the Fleſh, and Satan's will,</l>
                  <l>And labour for Salvation.</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49076:53"/>
                  <l>And may the Angels imitate,</l>
                  <l>And Saints that are in Heaven.</l>
                  <l>And ſuch obedience yeeld to Chriſt,</l>
                  <l>As ſhould to him be given</l>
                  <l>Give us this day our dayly bread</l>
                  <l>O Lord we thee intreat,</l>
                  <l>Give life and health, and cloathes and wealth,</l>
                  <l>And food for us to eat.</l>
                  <l>And give us grace, on thee to place,</l>
                  <l>Our truſt and confidence,</l>
                  <l>Till life doth end, let us depend,</l>
                  <l>Upon thy Providence,</l>
                  <l>Forgive our debts, as even we,</l>
                  <l>On debtors pity take,</l>
                  <l>Remit our ſins and blot them out,</l>
                  <l>For Jeſus Chriſt his ſake,</l>
                  <l>And lead us not into temptation,</l>
                  <l>But free us from all evil,</l>
                  <l>And grant to us thy preſervation,</l>
                  <l>From World, and fleſh, and Devill.</l>
                  <l>Now unto thee, all prayſes be,</l>
                  <l>O Lord that didſt elect,</l>
                  <l>Us to ſalvation, before Creation,</l>
                  <l>And others didſt reject.</l>
                  <l>Lord thy free Grace, in this great caſe,</l>
                  <l>Moſt plainly doth appear,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch as we, ſhould ſaved be,</l>
                  <l>And Chriſt our ſcores ſhould clear.</l>
                  <l>O bleſſed Son, thou haſt well done,</l>
                  <l>To die for thine Elected,</l>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:49076:54"/>
                  <l>For thou waſt ſlain, and ſufferedſt pain,</l>
                  <l>That we might be protected.</l>
                  <l>Great was thy merit, with holy ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Thou fully waſt anoynted,</l>
                  <l>And full of Grace, fit for the place,</l>
                  <l>Thy Father had appointed.</l>
                  <l>To mediate and undertake,</l>
                  <l>For us poor ſinful creatures,</l>
                  <l>Thy Fathers will thou didſt fulfil,</l>
                  <l>And didſt aſſume our natures.</l>
                  <l>And in due time the Croſs did'ſt Climb,</l>
                  <l>And ſuffered'ſt grievous pain,</l>
                  <l>Waſt after dead and buried,</l>
                  <l>And then didſt riſe again.</l>
                  <l>And through the skie to Heaven high,</l>
                  <l>Unto a glorious place,</l>
                  <l>Then didſt thou go, and mount up to,</l>
                  <l>Thy Fathers Throne of Grace.</l>
                  <l>And reconcile that bloody broile,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin procured,</l>
                  <l>Which being done, by Gods own ſon,</l>
                  <l>His Saints are all ſecured.</l>
                  <l>Thou art indeed, the womans ſeed,</l>
                  <l>That broke the Serpents head,</l>
                  <l>And with a flood, of thy own blood,</l>
                  <l>A Pardon purchaſed.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacrifice, did pay the price,</l>
                  <l>For us poor ſinful creatures,</l>
                  <l>Lord thou didſt dye, and ſatisfie,</l>
                  <l>Sin ſuffered in our natures.</l>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:49076:54"/>
                  <l>O bleſſed ſon, ſince thou haſt done,</l>
                  <l>This mighty work of merit,</l>
                  <l>The ſame apply effectnally,</l>
                  <l>By thy moſt holy ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>That thy redeem'd may be eſteem'd,</l>
                  <l>By God and godly men,</l>
                  <l>Thou bleſſed ſon, O ſtill go on,</l>
                  <l>And interceade for them,</l>
                  <l>In thy good word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou doſt record,</l>
                  <l>A perfect Declaration,</l>
                  <l>To all thy ſons, and choſen ones,</l>
                  <l>Of 'th miſteries of Salvation.</l>
                  <l>Now in their hearts, and inner parts,</l>
                  <l>Work by thy ſpirit in them,</l>
                  <l>Obedience, that they from hence,</l>
                  <l>May live like holy men.</l>
                  <l>By thy Dominion overcome,</l>
                  <l>Their Enemies O Lord,</l>
                  <l>And to that end, be pleas'd to ſend,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſpirit with thy word.</l>
                  <l>To good and bad, we freewil had,</l>
                  <l>But now ſince <hi>Adam's</hi> fall,</l>
                  <l>It is not ſo, to will or do,</l>
                  <l>We are unable all.</l>
                  <l>We are both dead and buried,</l>
                  <l>Till thou ſhalt us tranſlate,</l>
                  <l>Till thou convert, and bring the heart,</l>
                  <l>Into a gracious ſtate.</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall we be, for ever free,</l>
                  <l>From our old natures clogg,</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:49076:55"/>
                  <l>And from the ſin that we are in,</l>
                  <l>And freely ſerve our God.</l>
                  <l>And in a caſe, that (by his grace)</l>
                  <l>We ſhall have power and skill,</l>
                  <l>Both readily and ſpiritually,</l>
                  <l>Good works to do or will,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill the breed, of the old ſeed,</l>
                  <l>Of Unregeneration,</l>
                  <l>In us remains, till mortal pains,</l>
                  <l>Remove our earthly ſtation.</l>
                  <l>And we enjoy in heaven high,</l>
                  <l>The Saints felicity,</l>
                  <l>Then we ſhall be, made fully free,</l>
                  <l>To do good perfectly.</l>
                  <l>In the mean time, thoſe that are thine,</l>
                  <l>And Heaven ſhall inherit,</l>
                  <l>O gracious Lord, call by thy word,</l>
                  <l>And by thy holy ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>Out of the ſin, that they are in,</l>
                  <l>Into a ſtate of grace,</l>
                  <l>Through Chriſt thy Son, let it be done,</l>
                  <l>For thy own mercies ſakè,</l>
                  <l>O Lord give light, to blind, give ſight,</l>
                  <l>Remove their hearts of ſtone,</l>
                  <l>And hearts of fleſh, good and upright,</l>
                  <l>Lord give them in the Room,</l>
                  <l>Renew their wills, and give them Grace,</l>
                  <l>By'd them renewed be,</l>
                  <l>Lord give them grace, to grow apace,</l>
                  <l>For Lord thy grace is free.</l>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:49076:55"/>
                  <l>And there is none, but thee alone,</l>
                  <l>Can give this ſpecial grace,</l>
                  <l>Thou offereſt it, and mak'ſt us fit</l>
                  <l>Thy offer to imbrace,</l>
                  <l>This is our caſe, 'tis thy free grace,</l>
                  <l>And thy free grace alone,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not for any grace in us,</l>
                  <l>That was foreſeen or known.</l>
                  <l>Lord pierce our hearts, and inner parts,</l>
                  <l>We are but paſſive all,</l>
                  <l>Let thy good ſpirit, for thy ſons merit,</l>
                  <l>Give us an innward call.</l>
                  <l>O Lord accept, (us) thine elect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lord freely juſtifie,</l>
                  <l>Us thy poor Saints, Lord hear our plaints,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſon for us did dye.</l>
                  <l>He paid the debt, remov'd the lett,</l>
                  <l>He ſuffered for our ſin,</l>
                  <l>O for his ſake, Lord pitty take,</l>
                  <l>We do rely on him,</l>
                  <l>Lord we beleive for ſin we greive,</l>
                  <l>Lord help our unbeleif.</l>
                  <l>Let thy free Grace, good Lord take place,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſav'ſt the ſinful theif,</l>
                  <l>Adopt us ſons and ſet us free,</l>
                  <l>(Us for thy children take)</l>
                  <l>Not for the works that we have done</l>
                  <l>But for Chriſt Jeſus ſake.</l>
                  <l>Give us acceſs, to make addreſs,</l>
                  <l>Unto the Throne of grace.</l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:49076:56"/>
                  <l>Let us repent, cry and lament,</l>
                  <l>Our ſad and ſinful caſe,</l>
                  <l>O Lord accept, do not reject,</l>
                  <l>Our Prayers, and tears and cry,</l>
                  <l>Adopt us Heirs, for thy ſons ſake,</l>
                  <l>Who for our ſins did die.</l>
                  <l>Give us new hearts, and better parts,</l>
                  <l>Then ere we had before,</l>
                  <l>Let ſins dominion in us all,</l>
                  <l>Be weakned more and more,</l>
                  <l>Our ſeveral luſts, deſtroy in us,</l>
                  <l>Corruptions mortifie,</l>
                  <l>Let us more practice Holineſs,</l>
                  <l>And dayly ſin deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>Let ſaving faith, in us be wrought,</l>
                  <l>(Good Lord) moſt perfectly,</l>
                  <l>Let us into, the way be brought,</l>
                  <l>Of true felicity.</l>
                  <l>Increaſe this grace, in us apace,</l>
                  <l>O multiply it more,</l>
                  <l>This maſter grace, deſerves the place,</l>
                  <l>Increaſe it (Lord) therefore.</l>
                  <l>And let it work, by love alwaies,</l>
                  <l>In us, and every one,</l>
                  <l>Producing fruits of Holineſs,</l>
                  <l>Faith never goes alone.</l>
                  <l>By word and Prayer, and Sacraments,</l>
                  <l>Let it increaſed be,</l>
                  <l>Let us be juſtifi'd by it,</l>
                  <l>And ſav'd eternally,</l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49076:56"/>
                  <l>O Gracious Lord, let us accord,</l>
                  <l>To all the truths that be,</l>
                  <l>Revealed in the written Word,</l>
                  <l>For all Poſterity.</l>
                  <l>Lord let our hearts, and inner parts,</l>
                  <l>By faith be purifi'd,</l>
                  <l>And by that Sword, thy Holy Word,</l>
                  <l>Let ſin be mortifi'd.</l>
                  <l>Give us deſire, with hearts intire,</l>
                  <l>To love thee cordially,</l>
                  <l>O give us grace, that track to trace,</l>
                  <l>That leads to bliſs and joy.</l>
                  <l>Some crumbs of comfort, Lord we crav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our faith is very weak,</l>
                  <l>We almoſt are brought to deſpair,</l>
                  <l>O let thy ſpirit ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>A word of comfort to our hearts,</l>
                  <l>In this our miſery.</l>
                  <l>Let us from hence, have perfect ſence,</l>
                  <l>Of our felicity.</l>
                  <l>We (<hi>Agar</hi> like) have loſt our ſight,</l>
                  <l>And now are in diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Remove the ſcales, Lord give us light</l>
                  <l>To ſee our happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Lord we Repent, and do lament,</l>
                  <l>Our infidelity,</l>
                  <l>O make our faith more evident,</l>
                  <l>Remove our malady.</l>
                  <l>The well of life it open lies,</l>
                  <l>Yet we no comfort find,</l>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:49076:57"/>
                  <l>We water want, for want of Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Our feares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our Faith do blind.</l>
                  <l>Therefore O Lord, grant unto us</l>
                  <l>Aſſurance of Salvation,</l>
                  <l>O clear our ſtates, from all miſtakes,</l>
                  <l>And free us from Damnation.</l>
                  <l>And when we ſuch aſſurance have,</l>
                  <l>Grant we may carefully,</l>
                  <l>Preſerve the ſame, and praiſe thy name,</l>
                  <l>And live Religiouſly.</l>
                  <l>Thy Church and People, Lord protect,</l>
                  <l>From all their Enemies,</l>
                  <l>Be graci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s is Lord, to thine Elect,</l>
                  <l>Hear their complaints and cryes.</l>
                  <l>O bleſs the King and councel him,</l>
                  <l>His Royal Spouſe direct</l>
                  <l>And in her heart, and every part,</l>
                  <l>True Holineſs erect.</l>
                  <l>Lord bleſs Duke <hi>Iames,</hi> let all his aims,</l>
                  <l>Be for thy Glory bent,</l>
                  <l>Bleſs all the Royal Family,</l>
                  <l>And guide the Parliament.</l>
                  <l>Remove the wicked from the King,</l>
                  <l>His godly Councel bleſs,</l>
                  <l>Eſtabliſh Lord the Throne of him,</l>
                  <l>And (his) in Righteouſneſs.</l>
                  <l>O fit us all both great and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>To meet our Bleſſed Lord,</l>
                  <l>When he ſhall come, and juſtly Doom</l>
                  <l>And ſentence all the world.</l>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:49076:57"/>
                  <l>When he ſhall ſit, let us be quit.</l>
                  <l>And cleared from damnation,</l>
                  <l>By Faith in him, that dy'd for ſin,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe our ſalvation.</l>
                  <l>Lord, when this dreadful day will come,</l>
                  <l>To us it is unknown,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts by decree, and known to thee,</l>
                  <l>And unto thee alone.</l>
                  <l>Let's watch and pray, both night and day,</l>
                  <l>Therefore moſt fervently,</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt may ſay at that great day,</l>
                  <l>You have dealt faithfully.</l>
                  <l>You have well done, O therefore come,</l>
                  <l>And enter into joy.</l>
                  <l>Receive a Crown, with great renown,</l>
                  <l>Bliſs and Felicity.</l>
                  <l>Lord hear our Prayers, accept our Tears,</l>
                  <l>And pitty on us take,</l>
                  <l>Not for our worth, which merits wrath,</l>
                  <l>But for Chriſt Jeſus ſake.</l>
                  <l>To Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>By Angels, and by men,</l>
                  <l>All Power and Glory be aſcrib'd,</l>
                  <l>For ever more, Amen.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poems">
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:49076:58"/>
                     <head>An Epitaph upon the death of the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful <hi>Anne Cokaine</hi> Widdow, who Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt 1664.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <byline>By Edward Manlove <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                     </byline>
                     <l>HEre lies inter'd, one that deſerv'd,</l>
                     <l>Great Honour, Praiſe and Fame,</l>
                     <l>Who comely was, and did ſurpaſs,</l>
                     <l>Moſt of her Noble Name.</l>
                     <l>In liberallity, and Hoſpitallity,</l>
                     <l>This Lady did delight,</l>
                     <l>O Muſes riſe, do not deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>Her praiſes to indite,</l>
                     <l>Yea ring her knell, her praiſes tell,</l>
                     <l>She humble was, though great,</l>
                     <l>Her comly parts, and humble heart,</l>
                     <l>Her prayſes may compleat.</l>
                     <l>A comly Creature for form and feature,</l>
                     <l>Proper and tall of ſtature,</l>
                     <l>Noble by Birth, lies in the earth,</l>
                     <l>Death conquer'd comly nature.</l>
                     <l>This Flower was, cut down like Graſs,</l>
                     <l>Which flouriſhed many a day,</l>
                     <l>She quit the Stage, in her old age,</l>
                     <l>Grimm Death, took life away.</l>
                     <l>God call'd for her, ſhe made no ſtir,</l>
                     <l>But yeilded patiently,</l>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49076:58"/>
                     <l>She knew full well, none need her tell,</l>
                     <l>All mortal men muſt die.</l>
                     <l>To Rich and Poor, reſpect ſhe bore,</l>
                     <l>She did no ſort deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>She patiently did live and die,</l>
                     <l>And ſo ſhe clos'd her eyes.</l>
                     <l>Now in the Duſt (as all we muſt)</l>
                     <l>Ere long interred be,</l>
                     <l>This Lady is, Lord bring to Bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Her whole Poſterity.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>An Epitaph upon the Death of Mr. <hi>William Waine,</hi> Vicar of <hi>ASHBORN.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <byline>
                        <hi>Compoſed by Edward Manlove</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                     </byline>
                     <l>SInce that pale death, hath ſtopt the breath,</l>
                     <l>Of Learned <hi>William Wain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Friends and Allies, dry your wet eyes,</l>
                     <l>To Weep it is in vain.</l>
                     <l>He's in the Duſt, where all men muſt,</l>
                     <l>Ere long interred be,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt he liv'd here, he did appear,</l>
                     <l>A Learned man to be.</l>
                     <l>Of judgement great, tho not ſo neat,</l>
                     <l>In words, as many are,</l>
                     <l>But for his parts, in learned Arts,</l>
                     <l>With moſt, he might compare.</l>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:49076:59"/>
                     <l>Yet they can tell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that knew him well,</l>
                     <l>He was not puff'd with Pride,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſoared high, ambitiouſly,</l>
                     <l>But humbly liv'd and dy'd.</l>
                     <l>And in his Grave, as in a Cave,</l>
                     <l>This learned <hi>Rabby</hi> lies,</l>
                     <l>Where he muſt ſtay, till that great day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>That Chriſt ſhall ſay ariſe.</l>
                     <l>Then Learned <hi>Wain,</hi> muſt riſe again,</l>
                     <l>From duſty earth and Clay,</l>
                     <l>To judgement juſt, (as all men muſt)</l>
                     <l>And after live for aye.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>Books newly Printed for <hi>Richard Mills</hi> at the <hi>Peſte</hi> and <hi>Morter</hi> without <hi>Temble Bar.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PAndion and Amphigenia,</hi> or the Hiſtory of the Coy Lady in large Octavo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Divine Contentment,</hi> or a Medicine for a Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man, in ſmall Octavo.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49076:59"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
